<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Lydia's heart opened: or, divine mercy magnified in the conversion of a sinner by the Gospel Being the sum of several sermons preaced lately by James Strong, M.A. and Minister of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Strong, James, 1618 or 19-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5993</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232916</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900241</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900241</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133432</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94063)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133432)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2557:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Lydia's heart opened: or, divine mercy magnified in the conversion of a sinner by the Gospel Being the sum of several sermons preaced lately by James Strong, M.A. and Minister of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Strong, James, 1618 or 19-1694.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 101, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by A.M. for Edward Brewster at the Crane in Pauls-Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: J. S.</note>
                  <note>With two final advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Preaching --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature, English --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conversion --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:133432:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133432:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LYDIA'S</hi> Heart Opened: OR, DIVINE MERCY Magnified in the Conversion of a Sinner BY THE GOSPEL Being the ſum of ſeveral SERMONS Preached lately by <hi>James Strong,</hi> M. A. and Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Nullum eſt peccatum, quod ſi non fecerim tu fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſti; ſi abſtinuerim, tu juſſiſti, &amp; quod tibi crediderim, gratiam tu infundiſti.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Auguſt. Lib. Soliloquiorum, Cap. 15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Jeſus the Author and finiſher of our faith,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 12.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>That no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence; But let him that glorieth glory in the Lord,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 1. ult.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Edward Brewſter</hi> at the <hi>Crane</hi> in <hi>Pauls-Church-Yard, 1675.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:133432:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:133432:2"/>
            <head>To the Religious Mrs. <hi>Mary Speke</hi> of <hi>Whitelackington,</hi> the Author wiſheth a confluence of Spiritual bleſſings in our dear Lord Jeſus.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe few notes following were preacht but with an ordinary intention, but thorow Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine mercy, both with your ſelf and others found more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary reception; ſo oftimes I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved when there is leaſt of mans ſtrength, there is moſt of Gods. Many have been too wiſe, and too mighty to do Gods work; but never any too foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh or too weak that have been imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him. The Word is that ſpiritual ſword wherewith God wounds the hearts
<pb facs="tcp:133432:3"/>of his enemies; but as <hi>Scanderbeg's</hi> Sword could do nothing without <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbeg's</hi> Arm; no more can this ſword, unleſs it be weilded by the arm of Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency. The reaſon why men do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve our report, is, becauſe the arm of the Lord is not revealed, <hi>Iſa. 53.1.</hi> Sure I have reaſon to hope, that that day when we diſcourſed of Gods opening <hi>Lydia</hi>'s, there were many other hearts opened alſo. My Notes which were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by your ſelf, and ſeveral others, I could not ſo eaſily do by tranſcribing them as by publiſhing them. And though Truth need no Apology, yet I muſt tell the world, that this had been as like to have ſlept in darkneſs, as many other Exerciſes have, had not the more than ordinary ſucceſs wherewith God atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it in preaching, provoked me to this ſervice.</p>
            <p>Miniſters are by Chriſt called ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Fiſhers; a buſie imployment, full of toyl and danger, ſith the place of fiſhing is not a ſhallow ſtream, but a raging and tumultuous ſea, in which after we have tired our ſelves, and ſpent
<pb facs="tcp:133432:3"/>our strength, nothing ſo breaks our hearts as this, that we labour all night and catch nothing. But Oh if at laſt we caſt out the Net, and incloſe a multitude, 'tis no wonder we are not able to bear our own joy, being aſtoniſhed as <hi>Peter, Luk. 5.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> excuſe my boldneſs in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixing your Name to this ſmall Manual. And indeed I had not had confidence, but that I preſume you have with that other <hi>Mary</hi> ſate too long at Chriſts feet, to be aſhamed of Chriſts Truth. What inward comforts ſoever God hath given you by your conſtant and diligent at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance on his Worſhip, give God the glory; a dram of that ſweetneſs that flows from the upper ſprings, will allay the bitterneſs of thoſe Mara-like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters wherewith God drenches his deareſt Servants. For our part whom God hath intruſted with the Myſteries of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, though we are on every ſide op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, yet 'tis mercy we are not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt under all other hardſhips; we have yet cauſe to bleſs God, who hath not taken the Word of Truth utterly
<pb facs="tcp:133432:4"/>out of our mouth. He never well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood what, the calling of a Miniſter was, that thinks ſtrange of any ſuffering in the ſervice of Chriſt. It would well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Miniſters mouth what <hi>Pompey</hi> once replied to the Mariners, who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded him from ſailing in a ſtorm, when he was imployed for bringing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion to <hi>Rome,</hi> under a ſtrait Siege; <hi>'Tis neceſſary that</hi> Rome <hi>be relieved, but 'tis not neceſſary that we ſhould live.</hi> Sure 'tis neceſſary that Chriſts ſheep be fed, but 'tis not neceſſary that we ſhould live.</p>
            <p>The ſubject of theſe few Papers is of incomparable weight. The more I know my own heart and its deceits, the more jealous I am of others: Oh what a wily enemy do we carry in our own boſoms! How many treacherous reaches hath it to ruin our Immortal ſouls! <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> ſeemed zealouſly to deſire the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and would have bought it at a great price; but this poyſoned his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that his heart was not right in the ſight of God. Ah what faint and frigid ſervices do we bring before God,
<pb facs="tcp:133432:4"/>while we ſerve him with our mouths<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and honour him with our lips, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move our heart far from him? 'Tis true till the heart be renewed, God will have none of it; but when once 'tis renewed, it makes every thing elſe to be accepted. 'Tis the ſame to all other ſervices that <hi>Benjamin</hi> was to his Brethren, and there is no ſeeing Gods face without it. Oh how ſad were it, if at laſt we ſhould ſpoil all our ſervices and ſufferings by doing good duties with bad hearts. For preventing which danger we have cauſe to bleſs God for the labours of many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregious ſervants of his, who have left the Church a rich treaſury of inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, into which if by caſting my mite I may in any meaſure ſerve the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus and his People, 'tis more than ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient recompence to him, who ſubſcribes himſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, in the ſervice of the Goſpel, <hi>J. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:133432:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:133432:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Act. 16.14.</hi>
                  </bibl> And a certain woman named <hi>Lydia,</hi> a ſeller of Purple, of the City of <hi>Thyati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> which worſhipped God, heard us: whoſe heart the Lord opened that ſhe attended to the things which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in the Evangeliſts we have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chriſti,</hi> the Records of the Acts of Chriſt, while he was converſant on the Earth; ſo in this Book we have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Apoſtolorum,</hi> the Acts of the Apoſtles. In which Hiſtory we have a lively repreſentation of the ſtate of the Church, while ſhe was young and in her Gradle, her increaſe and growth; what was the Doctrine of the Apoſtles, with what holy boldneſs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:133432:6"/>they preached Chriſt in the midſt of a thouſand troubles and torments; here we may read what was the fruit of the Goſpel, and how it got growth in the world in deſpight of all oppoſition; as alſo what is the difference between true Doctrine and falſe, with what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and ſubtilty falſe Apoſtles oppoſe the true, what reſt and breathings God gave his Church, and never was wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for her protection and preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>This Hiſtory by the conſent of all bears date from the Aſcenſion of Chriſt unto the firſt year of <hi>Paul</hi>'s coming to <hi>Rome,</hi> which was the ſpace of twenty-three years, in which we have a clear proof of the exact performance of all the Promiſes Chriſt made his Apoſtles; as of ſending them his Spirit, induing them with power from on high, the calling of the Gentiles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But not to carry you back further than is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, we read <hi>ver.</hi> 9. of this Chapter, that <hi>Paul</hi> by the Miniſtry of an Angel is called to <hi>Macedonia.</hi> A <hi>Viſion ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to Paul in the night, there ſtood a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:133432:6"/>man of Macedonia and prayed him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Come into Macedonia and help us.</hi> Where by the way we may note, that Miniſters, how meanly ſoever eſteemed in the world, are thoſe by whom God helps his periſhing people. This title the Apoſtle owns, a helper of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples joy, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. Thoſe that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not help themſelves ſometimes, can yet help others, poor themſelves, yet make many rich. <hi>Luther</hi> boldly told the Prince of <hi>Saxony (Scire te velim, &amp;c.)</hi> I would have your Highneſs know you have more need of my Prayers than I have of your Protection.</p>
            <p>Well, now it appears indeed that Chriſt by his death hath pulled down the wall of partition between Jew and Gentile, and that God hath put no difference between us and them; for what was <hi>Macedonia</hi> at this time when <hi>Paul</hi> was called to preach Chriſt there, but a maſs and mixture of Ignorance and Atheiſm, as we and other Gentiles were without God, without Chriſt, and without hope, <hi>Eph<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 2.12.</p>
            <p>Being come to <hi>Macedonia</hi> he begun
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:133432:7"/>to preach at <hi>Philippi, ver.</hi> 12. and his encouragements at firſt were but mean, for his auditory were only a few poor Women, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. <hi>Gualter</hi> on the place excellently notes, how God exerciſes the faith and conſtancy of his Servants. <hi>Paulus vocatus per Angelum: putaret aliquis omnes ei obviam venturas, &amp;c. Paul</hi> was called by an Angel, who would not have thought, that the whole Country would have flocked to hear ſuch a Preacher? But alas <hi>Paul</hi>'s hopes fail him, not one man came to hear the great Apoſtle, only a few poor Women, and among theſe God ſingles out one, and marks her up for mercy, <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>A certain woman named Lydia, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have here then the Hiſtory of <hi>Lydia</hi>'s Converſion; and here again we have,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Apoſtle preaching.</item>
               <item>2. A weak Woman hearing.</item>
               <item>3. The great God bleſſing the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Or we hare, 1. The perſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetted, who is ſeveral ways deſcribed.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:133432:7"/>
            <list>
               <item>1. By her Name to confirm the truth of the ſtory; <hi>Lydia.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. By her Sex, a Woman; that Sex by which ſin entered into the world.</item>
               <item>3. By her imployment; a ſeller of Purple; a trade (as one obſerves) ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not ſo much for neceſſity as for pride.</item>
               <item>4. By the place of her abode; a ſtranger, one of <hi>Thyatira</hi> a City of <hi>Lydia:</hi> all theſe difficulties God breaks thorough; humane improbabilities are no prejudice to Omnipotency. Though we are by nature like the Prodigal, are run into a far Country, yet our Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father can eaſily bring us home.</item>
               <item>5. She's deſcribed by her Religion, ſhe was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a Worſhipper of God.</hi> A Gentile ſhe was, yet ſome dark notions ſhe had of God, which ſhe got either by the light of nature, or by tradition from her fore-fathers, or ſome familiar acquaintance with the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſuch another as <hi>Cornelius</hi> was, <hi>Act.</hi> 10. But whatever dark apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſhe had of God, yet ſhe fell far ſhort of a Chriſtian, for till the heart
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:133432:8"/>be made good ground and purified by Faith, 'tis impoſſible it can bear good fruit,</item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">2ly. We have the means of her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Paul</hi> Preaches.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Lydia</hi> heard the Word.</item>
               <item>3. God makes the Word effectual, he opens her heart.</item>
            </list>
            <p>'Tis this latter part of the verſe that I deſign for the ſubject of my diſcourſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the means of <hi>Lydia</hi>'s Converſion, <hi>God opened the heart of Lydia, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt thing that I ſhall note is this:</p>
            <p>Doct. 1. <hi>That 'tis Gods work to open mans heart.</hi> God may and doth uſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour means to knock, but none can open but himſelf. Gods word in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is called a hammer, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.29. With this God beats and knocks at the door of our hearts, but no heart opens, unleſs it be held in the hand of his own Spirit; hence is that complaint of the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.1. <hi>Lord, who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved our report, and to whom hath the arm of the Lord been revealed!</hi> No won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:133432:8"/>that men believe not the report of the Goſpel, whilſt God doth not put forth or make bare his own arm.</p>
            <p>But for methods ſake, in proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Concluſion, I ſhall obſerve this order.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. I ſhall ſhew what's meant by the heart.</item>
               <item>2. What 'tis to open the heart.</item>
               <item>3. I ſhall prove that 'tis Gods work to open the heart.</item>
               <item>4. Shew why God opens the heart.</item>
               <item>5. Anſwer an Objection.</item>
               <item>6. Laſtly, come to Application.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Then let us enquire what is meant by the heart; and here to paſs by the various ſignifications of the Word in Scripture, by heart here we are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the rational Soul, with the faculties and affections which are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; for as the heart is the fountain of Natural life, ſo 'tis of Spiritual. This is the womb wherein Chriſt is firſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10. <hi>For with the heart man believeth unto righteouſneſs, ſc.</hi> Here faith is ſeated, here its born and breaths its firſt breath, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.37.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:133432:9"/>
               <hi>Philip</hi> to the Eunuch, <hi>If thou believeſt with all thine heart, thou maiſt be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</hi> There is no leſs in that zealous Prayer of the Apoſtle for his <hi>Epheſians, chap.</hi> 3.17. where he is upon his knees to the God of Heaven, <hi>that Chriſt may dwell in their hearts by faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us inquire what 'tis to open the heart. In ſhort, to open the heart is to convert a ſoul, or to turn a ſinner from the power of darkneſs unto God. The word in the Original that is here uſed, ſignifies properly to open a door: Now our hearts in Scripture as they are uſually called doors, ſo by nature they are all ſhut, and that under three ſeveral locks, and God in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion opens them all.</p>
            <p>There is one lock or bar of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and this is Gods firſt work to open our underſtanding: by nature we are very darkneſs it ſelf, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.8. Like that poor man born ſpiritually blind, thick cataracts there are upon all our eyes , unleſs God touch them with the hand of his Grace, and ſay, <hi>Ephphata,</hi> be opened. Now as the firſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:133432:9"/>creature that God made in the firſt Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation was Light, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. ſo 'tis in the new Creation he commands light to ſhine out of darkneſs. Oh the groſs and rude notions and apprehenſions that we have by nature of the moſt fundamental Truths or the Goſpel! How hardly are we perſwaded that by nature we are in the gall of bitterneſs, and in the bonds of iniquity? tell a poor ſinner that he is the ſervant of ſin, he'l reply as the <hi>Jews,</hi> he was never in bondage to any man. How hardly were the Diſciples themſelves perſwaded that Chriſts Kingdom was any other than an earthly Kingdom! With what difficulty were they brought to believe that their Lord and Maſter was riſen? nor had they at laſt, had not Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf opened their underſtandings, that they might underſtand the Scriptures, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.45. O rich mercy! O Divine work! The Preacher tells us, <hi>'Tis a good thing for the eyes to ſee the light;</hi> What a mercy is it then when Chriſt opens blind eyes to ſee the wonderful things contained in his Law, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.18.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:133432:10"/>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond bar or bolt that by nature is upon our hearts is ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, this ſticks to our wills; man by nature is a way ward and a ſelf-will'd creature, our wills are imbondaged to ſin, and though we have a will to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory our ſelves, yet we have none to ſave our ſelves. Corrupt minds know no other law but their own luſts; and of theſe they cry out as <hi>Iſrael</hi> of their Idols, <hi>Strangers have we loved, and ſtrangers will we follow,</hi> Jer. 2.25. When Chriſt comes and knocks at our hearts, corruption preſently riſes to oppoſe him, we will not have this man to reign over us, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.14. But God comes with his key and opens this door alſo; he makes us of an unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be a willing people, <hi>Pſal</hi> 110.3. This God doth not by violence and compulſion, but in a ſweet and a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious way; he perſwades <hi>Japheth</hi> to dwell in the Tents of <hi>Shem, Gen.</hi> 9.27. God reaſons us out of our rebellion, making uſe of that excellent gift of reaſon wherewith he hath adorned his creature. And thus debates the caſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:133432:10"/>with him, What reaſon have you to forſake me who am a fountain of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving water, for broken ciſterns that will hold no water? Why will you die O houſe of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> When all was well between God and you, was it not better with you than now? Turn you, turn you therefore from your evil ways. Thus God treats man as a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable creature, and takes the hint of his own gifts wherewith he bath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed his creature.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There's one lock or bolt more which God opens, and that is the Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. Man by mature cannot delight in God nor love him, but when God woes in earneſt he wins our hearts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and engages all our affections to himſelf; ſo that we love nothing but God, or for God: for when once the Will is won, all is won. For the Will among other perfections of the Soul, hath the dominion over all the other faculties and affections, when therefore it hath fixt the deſires, or ſome good that is proportionable to the wideneſs of the heart, it uſeth its liberty for the choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:133432:11"/>of ſuch means as are moſt proper for the attaining of that good, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploys all the inſeriour faculties for the execution of theſe means. In ſhort, as ſoon as the Soul becomes raviſht with the apprehenſion of that infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that is in God, it's earneſtly drawn out to deſire union with him, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of his glory. So that now God is the adequate object of all our love, joy and deſire: and that this is no other but Gods work, ſee <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6. <hi>The Lord thy God will circumciſe thy heart, and the heart of thy ſeed to love the Lord thy God, with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoul, &amp;c.</hi> But this is more directly our next work.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third thing propoſed is to prove, that 'tis Gods work to open mans heart. He that made the heart can only open it, men may knock, but there's none can open and enter but God alone. We read in the <hi>Acts,</hi> when the Exorciſts undertook to caſt out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean ſpirits, the Devils anſwered, <hi>Jeſus we know, and Paul we know, but who are ye?</hi> Act. 19.15. 'Tis ſo here, lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:133432:11"/>than God owns his meſſengers, and ſtands by them, Sin and Satan tell us, God he knows, and Jeſus he knows, but who are you? A lively abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods dealing with his people in this caſe we have in <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. where Chriſt comes &amp; wooes his Church, and lays her open, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. but ſee what ſilly and ſinful excuſes ſhe makes to put off Chriſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. <hi>I have put off my coat, how ſhall I put it on?</hi> But Chriſt had a purpoſe to enter, and therefore we read <hi>ver.</hi> 4. <hi>He put in his hand by the hole of the door,</hi> and then her heart was affectioned toward him. What is this hand or finger of Chriſt, but the efficacy of his Spirit, whereby he puts back the boult, or unlocks the door of her heart, before ſhe could come and entertain him?</p>
            <p>Chriſt firſt bores and digs thorough the heart, and makes a paſſage for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to enter, and then comes in and takes poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>The arguments for proof follow, of which the firſt is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſ.</hi> 1. Our hearts by nature are all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:133432:12"/>by Satan, and ſtrongly fortified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and Chriſt, whence Chriſt thus frames his argument; <hi>That the ſtrong man armed keeps the houſe till a ſtronger than he comes and bind him,</hi> Mat. 12.29. Satan hath the poſſeſſion and will not leave his hold until he be over-powered; ſo much that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture imports, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Who hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered us from the powers of darkneſs,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hath delivered us by force; ſo ſtrong are his chains that nothing can break them but the hand of Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency; but Oh here is the happineſs of Chriſt's redeemed, that ſtronger is he that is in them, than he that is in the world! <hi>Thanks be to God who hath made us conquerors thorough our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> I Joh. 4.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſ.</hi> 2. If God come into the heart he enters the right way, he doth not climb up the walls, nor creep in at the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, ſuch an entrance is not for the honour of the King of Saints, and therefore he bids us open the everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting doors, <hi>&amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 24. as when a King enters a City, the gates are ſet
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:133432:12"/>wide open, or thrown off their hinges, to congratulate the Kings coming, and ta ſhew their joyful entertaining of their lawful Soveraign; ſuch an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance is Chriſts. God makes no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible entry, doth not break the houſe, or enter againſt his peoples will; no, he ſweetly ſubdues us, as he that opens with a key: now none but God hath a key to open thoſe doors, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.7. <hi>The Angel to the Church of Philadelphia, &amp;c. Thus ſaith he that hath the key of David, which openeth and no man ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</hi> 'Tis wonderful to ſee the ſtrongeſt hold, and moſt impregnable caſtle that from outward force is free and invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; yet 'tis but the turning of a key that preſently opens it, and gives en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance without blood or blows; ſo 'tis here, God oyls the lock, and turns the key, and the Soul opens.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſ.</hi> 3. All heart-work in order to Salvation (if it be effectual) is aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to God. Take a few Inſtances.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God ſearches the heart, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.10. <hi>I the Lord ſearch the heart, and try the reins;</hi> he only knows it that made
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:133432:13"/>it, even he whoſe eyes are like a flame of fire, that pierce to the bottom of hell. The wiles and wickedneſs, the depths and deceits of this member are ſo many, that the Prophet cried out, <hi>Who can know them?</hi> Jer. 17.9. Who? none but an Omniſcient God, before whoſe eyes all things are naked and bare.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God opens our hearts to our ſelves (ſo much as we know of them ſavingly), <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.2. God minds <hi>Iſrael</hi> of the tedious and tireſom travel of theirs thorow the Wilderneſs forty years, which was to humble them, and prove them, to know what was in their heart; not that God might know, but as <hi>Auſtin</hi> obſerves, <hi>Tentat ut ſciat, id eſt, ut ſcire nos faciat:</hi> God trys to know (that is) to make us and others know what is in our hearts. We are by nature as great ſtrangers to our hearts as <hi>Hazael,</hi> who when the Prophet told him, <hi>He ſhould burn Iſraels Cities with ſire, ſlay their young men with the ſword, daſh the infants againſt the ſtones, and rip up the women with child;</hi> He ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:133432:13"/>theſe cruelties, with this ſtrange queſtion, <hi>Is thy ſervant a dog, that I ſhould do this?</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 8.12. Such bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous cruelties ſeemed at this time too odious for <hi>Hazael;</hi> but afterward the event proved the Propheſie true, <hi>ch.</hi> 13. We all as little know our hearts as <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zael,</hi> or the depths of our own cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God alone melts and ſoftens the heart. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.19. he promiſeth to take away the heart of ſtone, and give a heart of fleſh. He that turns the flint into a fountain, and fetches water out of the hard rock, is only able to break a heart of ſtone, and to make it a <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dadrimmon,</hi> a very valley of tears.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He comforts the heart. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.14. after he hath brought his Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wilderneſs, then he promiſeth to ſpeak to her heart, ſuch comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble words as no man can ſpeak. When all other comforters, like <hi>Job</hi>'s, prove mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable comforters indeed, then God ſaith, <hi>I, even I, am he that comforteth thee,</hi> &amp;c. This is Gods propriety, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. <hi>He alone revives the ſpirit of the contrite,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:133432:14"/>
            <p n="5">5. He new-makes the heart. As there is no mending of a crackt Bell, but it muſt be new caſt. So 'tis with a corrupt heart, it muſt be new made, or there's nothing done. God begins (as it were) a new Creation when he converts a Soul. So prays the penitent <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal.</hi> 45.10. <hi>Create in me a new heart, O Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 4. The next thing is to ſhew, why God opens the heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In ſhort: It is to poſſeſs it, and to dwell in it. God hath two Houſes to dwell in; the upper houſe is heaven, the lower houſe is the hearts of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. <hi>Thus ſaith the high and excellent one that inhabiteth eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, whoſe name is the holy one, I dwell in the high and holy place, with him alſo that is of an humble ſpirit.</hi> We may here ſtand and wonder, that he whoſe nature is Majeſty, whoſe place is Immenſity, whoſe time is Eternity, whoſe life is Sanctity, whoſe power is Omnipotency, whoſe work is Mercy, whoſe wrath is Juſtice, and whoſe throne is Sublimity, ſhould yet delight
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:133432:14"/>to dwell in a poor humble and broken heart, <hi>[Trap in loc.].</hi> When <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> had built that famous Temple for the worſhip of God, he admires the infinite condeſcention of God, in ſtooping ſo low as to have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with ſinful men: 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.27. <hi>Is it true indeed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that God will dwell in the earth ?</hi> Lo, God yet hath more intimate converſe with poor believers; he indeed dwelleth not in Temples made with hands; no, the hearts of his people are Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, and of theſe he ſays indeed, <hi>here will I dwell for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> There is one objection againſt this concluſion, and 'tis this: It ſeems that man hath power to open his own heart; why elſe doth Chriſt Jeſus bid the Church to open? in <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2 <hi>Open to me my ſiſter,</hi> &amp;c. And in <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.20. <hi>If any man open, I will enter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I ſhall anſwer in the words of <hi>Peter Martyr, Dicimur aperire quate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus id Deus in nobis facit, nam is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit ut aperiamus.</hi> We are ſaid to open in that God makes us to open; for he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:133432:15"/>works all our works for us, and crowns them in us. <hi>Certum eſt nos facere quod facimus, ſed Deus facit ut faciamus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, man muſt not be idle but active in this great work (as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards we ſhall ſhew) but God ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more works (ſomewhat in the Soul, and leaves ſome impreſſion by his Spirit in the heart, which ſtirs up an endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſeek after him, and to open to him. In that 5th of <hi>Cant.</hi> the Church confeſſeth Chriſts fingers were firſt in the door, before her heart was affectioned toward him. Thus no man can come to Chriſt, unleſs the Father draw him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. And is it thus, that it is Gods work to open mans heart? It teaches then to abhor the execrable and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous invention of Free-will, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the <hi>Arminian</hi> brood take the Crown from Gods head, and ſet it on the Creatures; robbing God of the glory of his own grace, who is both <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the Author and Finiſher of the work of grace in his redeemed. Neither will it help them to grant on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:133432:15"/>that God hath a hand in renewing us as a Moral Agent, by propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only the goodneſs of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Grace, and perſwading us only by ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Arguments to imbrace it; for a Moral Agent works no real effect, but God works ſomething in us: the Church found ſome mirrh which Chriſt left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him dropping from his fingers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe opened to her beloved, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.5. The Apoſtle therefore reſolves all into the mighty power of God, even that power whereby he railed his Son Chriſt from the grave: <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.20: where he prays, that his <hi>Epheſians may know what the exceeding greatneſs of his power is toward them that believe, according to the working of his mighty power which he wrought in Chriſt when he raiſed him up from the grave.</hi> Now did God only perſwade Chriſt to riſe out of the grave? no, but he put forth his almighty power for the effecting thereof: for could the Soul of Chriſt, which for a while was ſeparated from his body, be brought again to that body but by the Almighty power of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:133432:16"/>God? well, the ſame power is exerted in raiſing a Soul dead in ſin to the life of Grace that was exerted in raiſing Chriſt Jeſus himſelf from the grave. The caſe may be thus exemplified, for as the Marigold opens her leaves to the Sun, yet the Sun firſt ſhines on it, and warms, it with its beams; 'tis ſo with us, we open willingly our hearts to God, but God firſt warms our hearts with the ſun-beams of his Grace; for without him we can do nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. It ſerves for ever to humble us, to conſider that natural wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs wherein we were born. The doors of our hearts are all ſhut by nature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and Chriſt, fenced and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with ſtrong corruptions attd ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful reſolutions to reſiſt God and his dear Son. We read <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.19. When Chriſt firſt appear'd to his Diſciples, after his Reſurrection, he came when the doors were ſhut. Such is our caſe when firſt he comes to viſit and awaken poor loſt Sinners, there's no room nor entrance for him till he make way for himſelf, by his own Almighty power.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:133432:16"/>This for ever ſhould abaſe us in our greateſt attainments of Grace, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and remember what we were by nature. 'Tis ſtoried of <hi>Willigis</hi> a poor mans ſon, the ſon of a Wheeler, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Biſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> when he was advanced to the honour of that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick, to ſuppreſs that pride which the greatneſs of his place expoſed him to, that he cauſed ſeveral Wheels to be hung up about his Chamber, with this inſcription, <hi>Memento Willigis unde eras:</hi> Remember <hi>Willigis</hi> from whence thou art. Oh that we could <hi>look back to the rock from whence we were hewnl &amp;c.</hi> we ſhould find that we are but the ſinful ſlime of rebellious Parents loyns. Thus God pricks that ſwelling tumor of pride in <hi>Iſrael</hi> to which ſhe was ſubject by her advancement, and bids her remember that a poor <hi>Syrian</hi> ready to periſh was her father, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.5. Whatever honours or excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies we have received by Chriſt; yet the Apoſtle tells us 'tis our duty, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that by <hi>nature we were chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath even as others,</hi> Eph. 2.3.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:133432:17"/>Here's a holy art to make the elder brother Corruption to ſerve the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Grace; a ſerious remembrance of our natural vileneſs may keep the ſoul humble in our greateſt attainments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. It informs us of the piercing power of Gods Word, however weak and contemptible in the eyes of carnal reaſon. Its ſound is heard in the ear, but its force is felt in the heart. <hi>Paul</hi> preaches and <hi>Felix</hi> trembles; <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon prickt the <hi>Jews</hi> to the heart, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37. This was the fruit of Chriſts dealing with his Church, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.4. as ſoon as ſhe felt his hand in the hole of the door, her very heart was affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned toward him; juſtly therefore 'tis called a ſharp two-edged ſword, <hi>&amp;c. Heb.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Eliſha</hi> had his ſword as well as <hi>Jehu.</hi> And God hews his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies by his Prophets, and ſlays them by the words of their mouth. This ſword is like <hi>Saul</hi>'s it, never returns empty; if it doth not deſtroy our ſins, it will deſtroy our ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. It cautions us againſt a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake. When we hear that 'tis Gods
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:133432:17"/>work to open mans heart, we are apt to conclude that God expect nothing from us. Take we heed we do not thus abuſe the grace of the Goſpel, God delights to improve his own gifts, he hath endowed man with the gift of Reaſon, and ſaves him as a Reaſonable Creature. And therefore though all means of Grace have their virtue and efficacy from God, and he alone is the principal cauſe and author of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Yet God expects when he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades that we conſent, when he wooes by his Word that we yield, leſt ſtriving with our Maker, we provoke him to deal with us as he did with the old World, when for their contumacy and impenitency he reſolved, that his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſhould no longer ſtrive with man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 5. The next Uſe therefore ſhall be of Counſel (or rather Command) in the name of the great God of Heaven and Earth, that when God by his Word calls to us from Heaven, and bids us open, that with a holy readineſs we open thoſe everlaſting doors. To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:133432:18"/>you to which duty I ſhall add theſe Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. So long as our hearts are ſhut againſt God, we our ſelves are ſhut out of all comfortable communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God. God delights in none but where he is entertained: mark that Scripture, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.20. <hi>If any man hear my voice and open the door, I will come in to him, and ſup with him.</hi> I'le feaſt that man with my Preſence, my Grace, my Comforts; this man only ſhall know indeed what is that plenty, rarity and variety which is in that feaſt of fat things that I have made in my holy mountain. To ſuch I will make known my ſelf; I'le take them into my imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, feed and feaſt them with my Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, they ſhall ſee my face and know by experience what 'tis to have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the Father, and with his Son. Now pray conſider, could you be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to live a few years in the World, and to hear only what a bleſſed thing it is to enjoy the love of God, and the light of his Countenance, the ſweet and ſoul-raviſhing Comforts of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:133432:18"/>and yet to live and die and go to your graves and never know nor taſte any of this ſpiritual ſweetneſs? this muſt be your caſe if your hearts be not opened.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. Conſider that God yet offers to open your hearts, though we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps have ſtopt our ears thouſands of times, yet he once more ſtands at the door and knocks, and cries, open, open. And I make my appeal to your own Conſciences (if there be any life or ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs in them) whether you find not God ſtriving to come in, while by the hammer of his Word he knocks and begs you by his Meſſenger to give your hearts to him. Is not God at this inſtant convincing ſome that he is a loſt periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing creature in himſelf? is he not ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you the incomparable excellency of Chriſt, and his al-ſufficiency to ſave Sinners? Oh how think you to eſcape if you neglect ſo great Salvation! you have heard of that fearful reſolution of God againſt the impenitent old World, when by the preaching of <hi>Noah</hi> a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years together God had perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:133432:19"/>them to repent, yet all to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe? what ſays God at laſt? <hi>My ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſhall not alway ſtrive with man.</hi> Oh when God ſtrives with us in mercy, and we ſtrive with God by impenitency 'tis ſad! <hi>Wo to him that thus ſtrives with his maker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, whatſoever was written afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time was written for our inſtruction. If we will not take example from the old world that is paſt, be ſure we ſhall make example to the new World that is to come, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. Conſider to whom 'tis we are to open, why 'tis to Chriſt, <hi>Open to me my ſiſter, &amp;c.</hi> an Emphatick word, and as <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Wheels were full of eyes, ſo is this word full of motives: To me that am thy Saviour, thy King, thy Prieſt, thy Prophet, thy Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom, thy Beloved, thy Brother; Ah who would not open to ſuch a one? As <hi>Laban</hi> ſaid to <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſervant, <hi>Come in thou bleſſed of the Lord, why ſtandeſt thou without?</hi> Gen. 24.31. ſo ſhould we ſay when he comes to our door; yea, as <hi>Lot</hi> preſſed the two Angels
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:133432:19"/>greatly when they ſeemed ſtrange, and overcame them with his importunity, that they came in, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.3. ſo ſhould we.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 4. Conſider Gods end in open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the heart, 'tis to dwell there; God dwelleth not in Temples made with hands, but as he hath choſen Heaven for his glorious Preſence, ſo he hath choſen the heart for his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Preſence, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.16. Neither will God come in empty, he brings Salvation and all other bleſſings with him; thus Chriſt told <hi>Zacheus,</hi> Luk. 19.9. <hi>This day is ſalvation come to thy houſe.</hi> There's nothing loſt by enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining this gueſt, where he comes his reward is with him; if <hi>Obed Edom</hi>'s houſe were bleſſed for entertaining Gods Ark, how bleſſed is that heart that opens and entertains God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf?</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſome may object that Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers have opened already, and that Chriſt dwells in them by faith, and ſith they have good evidences that they are ſuch, what need more ado for them?</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:133432:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There are divers degrees and meaſures of Grace whereby Chriſt dwells in his Elect; and though we have already opened to him, yet 'tis our duty to open wider ſtill. Our caſe is like that of the blind-man whom Chriſt cured in the Goſpel, who after the firſt touch ſaw men as trees walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but Chriſt touches his eyes again, and then he ſaw plainly, <hi>Mar.</hi> 8.25. 'Tis juſt ſo with the beſt of Gods Saints. Alas we have but a little of the Power and Spirit of Chriſt at our firſt acquaintance with him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt evermore widen our hearts, and make more room to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 5. Conſider the many engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments God hath laid upon us to open our hearts to him.</p>
            <p>God hath opened his heart to us, he hath not lockt up the Myſteries of the Goſpel in ſecreſie? No, as we read of <hi>Sampſon</hi> for the love he bore to <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lah</hi> he told her all his heart; ſo hath God to us, he hath kept nothing from us that may make us wiſe to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:133432:20"/>The Apoſtle tells the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> That <hi>he had ſhewed them all the counſel of God,</hi> Act. 20.27. And <hi>that the will of God was never revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to other ages as now it is revealed to us,</hi> Eph. 3.5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God hath opened Heaven to us, that for ſin was ſhut againſt all <hi>Adams</hi> poſterity: for as <hi>Adam</hi> ſinning was driven out of an Earthly Paradiſe, ſo was he alſo out of the Heavenly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe; and Chriſt came from Heaven, and ſuffered death for us that he might open a way for us again into Heaven, therefore he is called <hi>our forerunner, Heb.</hi> 6.20. <hi>Whither our forerunner is entered in for us.</hi> The Holy of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies in the Sanctuary was a type of Heaven, this holy place was ſevered or parted from the body of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary by a veil: at Chriſts death we read this veil rent in twain, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.51. hereby ſhewing us, that Chriſt by his death hath made an open way for us into the Holy of Holies in Heaven; God hath paved us a way in the blood of his Son, and now we may come with boldneſs.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:133432:21"/>
            <p n="3">3. God opens his ears to our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37.17. his eyes to diſtreſſes, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.7. <hi>I have ſurely ſeen the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of my people Iſrael, which are in Egypt, and have heard their cry, &amp;c.</hi> He hears his peoples prayers, and their enemies threats; he hears the railing of <hi>Rabſhekah,</hi> the curſing of <hi>Shimei,</hi> and the leaſt injuries that are plotted againſt the juſt, ſhall not we open our heart to him?</p>
            <p n="4">4. He hath opened hell and the grave for us: We read when Chriſt ſuffered, at the Reſurrection many dead bodies of the Saints which ſlept aroſe with him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.53. to aſſure us that he hath the keys of hell and of death, and that he will not leave the duſt of his Saints for ever under the power of death; No, <hi>I know thou wilt not leave my ſoul in the grave, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 16. The grave (until Chriſts Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection) was an impregnable hold, and from thence had been no redemption, had not Chriſt opened it for our deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance.</p>
            <p n="5">5. God opens his hand to us daily
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:133432:21"/>in the gifts of his bounty, God comes loaden with plenty of all good things. He openeth his hand and filleth every living thing with goodneſs; whatever wants the poor creature ſuſtains God alone ſupplys them all. Oh ſhall God open ſo much to us, and ſhall we not open our hearts to him? it would be horrid ingratitude, ſhould we thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite the Lord.</p>
            <p>The duty though moſt reaſonable yet it's difficult, theſe Directions im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved may make it eaſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Direct.</hi> 1. Be faithful and diligent in ſearching into the ſtate of your hearts, know that there are a thouſand de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits that lodg and lurk in the hearts of the ſons of men. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> tells us, <hi>That the ungodly boaſteth of his hearts deſire.</hi> When <hi>Solomon</hi> aſſures us, <hi>That the ſoul of the wicked deſireth evil, Prov.</hi> 21.10. O let not your treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous hearts deceive you , poſe your ſelves with ſuch ſerious Queſtions as theſe: Heart what is thy caſe? how is it with thee, tell me faithfully, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou art the old heart, or the new?
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:133432:22"/>whoſe Image doſt thou bear, Chriſts or Satans? Art thou a dead heart, or a living? haſt thou been ever new-made or no? haſt thou new affections, new motions and deſires or no? tell me, hath Chriſt taken poſſeſſion of thee or not? Theſe would be cloſe Queſtions if our hearts were held cloſly to anſwer them. <hi>Know you not</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that Chriſt is in you except you are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If you find not Chriſt within you, mourn over your empty hearts: What a lamentation did <hi>Mary</hi> make when ſhe found the grave empty, when ſhe ſought Chriſt, <hi>Ah they have taken away my Lord, &amp;c.</hi> Much more reaſon have we to break our hearts with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, if upon a ſerious ſearch we find not Chriſt in our heart: Oh cry out, Sin and Satan have robbed me of my dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Saviour, no tokens or footſteps of Chriſt to be ſeen in me.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Seek Chriſt diligently, imitate the Church in a like caſe, who ſought Chriſt Jeſus at home and abroad; by night upon her bed ſhe ſought him
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:133432:22"/>whom her ſoul loved, aroſe and went about the City and enquires of the Watchmen, and all to find her Beloved, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Be gleaning in Gods field; the Ordinances of God are a ſpiritual har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, where you may fill your empty ſacks, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did his Brethrens. <hi>Ruth</hi> gleaned in <hi>Boaz</hi>'s field among the ſheaves and reapers, and ſo returned laden. Chriſts Ordinances are like <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raels</hi> Camp, where the Heavenly Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na falls. If your ſouls are ſick of love to Chriſt, here he's preſent to refreſh you with flagons of ſpiritual liquor far better than wine. Take then Chriſts own counſel, get forth by the footſteps of the flock, and feed your kids be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the ſhepherds tents, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.8. The Prophet calls the Word a hammer; come under this hammer and there's hope of opening. Again, the word is Chriſt's voice, and 'tis worth our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that the Church firſt cried out, <hi>It is the voice of my Beloved that knocketh,</hi> before ſhe opened, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:133432:23"/>
            <p n="5">5. Affect your hearts with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable excellencies of Chriſt. We are all in a deep ſleep by nature, and who will riſe and open to one whom he doth not know? Obſerve when Chriſt ſollicited his Church, ſhe had never ſtirred out of that deep ſlumber ſhe was in, and opened to him, had ſhe not been thorowly convinced of thoſe rare endowments that were in him; witneſs that rare deſcription ſhe makes of him from the 10. <hi>v.</hi> to the end of that <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. the daughters of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> wondered ſhe troubled her ſelf ſo much about her Beloved, to whom ſhe replys, <hi>Do you wonder; my beloved is white and ruddy, and the chiefeſt among ten thouſand, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Labour for Faith as for Heaven it ſelf; as Faith empties the heart of ſin, ſo it opens the heart to Chriſt: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief bolts the door againſt him, but Faith unlocks it. Chriſt could not do many mighty works in <hi>Nazareth</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their unbelief; away then with all ſinful fears. Though we have many miſgivings within us, yet lament
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:133432:23"/>them with bitterneſs and cry out I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, Lord help my unbelief. Mind that bleſſed promiſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2l.22. <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever you ask believing, it ſhall be given you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Laſtly, get your hearts warmed with the grace of Love; though they are cold by nature, yet beg a ſpark of this Heavenly fire from Heaven. Love is of a dilating and widening nature it makes room in the heart for Chriſt, read <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.23. <hi>If any man love me, he will keep my word, and my Father will come to him, and we will dwell with him.</hi> Can we poſſibly bolt the door, and keep out him whom we love? no, the love of God will conſtrain us to let him in, and entertain him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. The word there uſed ſignifies to ſtreighten, or to keep in, but that is from other things as from ſin, and the world, that ſo the ſoul may be the more free for God: Oh then that the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of our love to Chriſt might be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond meaſure! this one rule, if practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, would do the work for all, God never parts from that ſoul where there
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:133432:24"/>is but love to entertain him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 6. Laſtly, its matter of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable comfort to as many as (with <hi>Lydia</hi>) have their hearts opened; Oh what heavenly peace and ſecurity, what rivers of ſpiritual pleaſure and joy ſhould overflow our hearts as ſoon as God hath opened them! Hath God opened thy heart? know that God hath brought Heaven into thy heart now, and the ſame God will bring thee into Heaven ſhortly. When <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi>'s heart was opened, how was her joy increaſed, and her affections en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged; we read ſhe ſought acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the Apoſtles, ſhe could no longer be a ſtranger to them who had been the inſtruments of her Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but beſought them earneſtly, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>If you have judged me faithful to the Lord, come into my houſe and abide there, and ſhe conſtrained us.</hi> Her heart could not hold her comfort but muſt now impart ſome of it to them, from whom ſhe had received it. If any of us have ſhared with <hi>Lydia</hi> in the Grace of the Goſpel, make a little
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:133432:24"/>room more in theſe narrow hearts of yours to entertain ſome part of her comforts alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> You will tell me you would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, but you doubt whether your heart be opened or no?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> For your reſolution, you may know that your heart is opened by God. If you find your love, and your affections carried out to God above all things, in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.2. where the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet deſcribes the New Jeruſalem. We read the Lord brought him to the Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate of the Sanctuary, and ſaid unto him, <hi>This gate ſhall be ſhut, and ſhall not be opened, and no man ſhall enter in by it, becauſe the Lord God of Iſrael hath entered by it.</hi> This gate is a figure of the heart, which being once opened to God muſt be opened to nothing elſe. We may know then that our heart is opened to God, when 'tis ſhut to all vanities in the world, God will have all the heart or none , nothing muſt ſhare with him; a heart poſſeſſed by God loves nothing but God or for God.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:133432:25"/>
            <p n="2">2. If our heart be opened to God, it will caſt out all ſin; as when the graves were opened at Chriſts death, we read they ſent forth their dead, the dead bodies aroſe, as ſoon as the graves were opened; ſo 'twill be in a ſoul that is opened to Chriſt, it will caſt out all dead works, works of ſin and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: <hi>If Chriſt be in you, the body is dead becauſe of ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. A heart opened to Chriſt will ſend forth all ſorts of ſpiritual Graces, duties and performances: as 'tis with the Earth while it lies bound up and frozen in the Winter, it's barren and brings forth nothing; but as ſoon as the ſpring warms it with the Sun, and opens it, it ſends forth all ſweet herbs and flowers; even thus we may know that Chriſt is within us by the Graces and gracious performances that are without. Chriſt is a living root, a root that never ceaſes, but like <hi>Aaron</hi>'s rod is always blooming and bloſſoming.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Where the heart is opened to Chriſt all is opened, all the parts and powers of the whole man God; is ſo
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:133432:25"/>entertained into one part, that he is kept out of none, 'tis all ſuitable where God hath opened the heart. A taſte you may have in theſe Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There's an open ear to hear the Word of God, till God hath taken poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the heart, we are like the deaf Adder that ſtop our ears to the voice of Gods ſweet charmers, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.18. <hi>In that day ſhall the deaf hear the words of this Book, and the eyes of the blind ſhall ſee out of obſcurity and darkneſs.</hi> (1) The blind and deaf Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, ſhall in the days of the Goſpel be both enlightned and enlivened with ſaving knowledg: whenſoever God commands men to return from iniquity, he openeth their ears to diſcipline, <hi>Job</hi> 36.10. Gods Word comes with autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and makes its own way to make room for Chriſt when once he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken hold of the heart.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There's an open eye to ſee the will and mind of God; we are all by nature as well blind as deaf in things that are ſpiritual, but God makes the eyes of the blind to ſee as well as the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:133432:26"/>ears of the deaf to hear, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.5. (that is) God ſo far enlightens our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, that the myſteries of Salvation are revealed and made clear to us. Gods Word comes now with a Commiſſion, when it goeth forth it gives light and underſtanding to the ſimple. Gods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed ſhall never miſcarry thorow ignorance. They have an unction from the holy one and know all things, 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 2.20. (1) Whatſoever is neceſſary to Salvation; in leſſer errors Believers may be intangled, but in Fundamentals they ſhall never. If any man be a doer of Gods will, he ſhall know of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine whether it be of God, <hi>Job.</hi> 7.17.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There's an open hand to do the work of God, ſuch whoſe hearts God hath opened are not only hearers of the Word but doers alſo; ſuch a one ſhews his Faith by his Works, you may ſee what ſuch a one is within by what he is without. Like. <hi>Noah</hi>'s Ark he is pitcht within and without, there's grace with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in and grace without, he ſhews by a good converſation his works in meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and wiſdom, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.13.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:133432:26"/>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, where God hath opened the heart, there is alſo an open mouth to praiſe God. This is added to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat the work, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.6. God promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to make the tongue of the dumb to ſing. Such ſouls whom God hath viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in mercy are not able to conceal either Gods mercies or their own com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts; no, they muſt ſpeak of the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving-kindneſs of God, though it be before Kings. They muſt bear a part with <hi>Zachary,</hi> though once dumb yet as ſoon as his tongue was looſed cried out, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael who hath viſited and redeemed his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> Luk. 1.68.</p>
            <p>And ſo much of the Author of <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi>'s Converſion, or that great work of God in opening <hi>Lydia</hi>'s heart; next let us conſider the means whereby'twas wrought, ſhe attended to the things which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake.</p>
            <p>What this attention of <hi>Lydia</hi> was, is worth inquiry, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The word here tranſlated <hi>attention,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies properly to give heed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſcil. animum,</hi> to apply the heart or mind to a thing.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:133432:27"/>
            <p>In the New Teſtament, the word is uſed in a double relation:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1ſt.</hi> To things hurtful.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2ly.</hi> To things uſefal.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To things hurtful, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15. <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The ſame word that is uſed here (that is) take heed that you avoid them, leſt you are inſnared by them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The word is uſed in relation to things uſeful, as in <hi>Act.</hi> 8.6. <hi>The people gave heed to the things that Philip ſpake,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the ſame word that is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed here; ſo <hi>Lydia</hi> attended or gave heed, or applied her heart to the things ſpoken by <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This heedful hearing is oppoſed to all manner of ſlighting, oppoſing, or turning away our ears from hearing the Word: ſuch hearers we read of <hi>Acts</hi> 13.45. <hi>The Jews filled with envy ſpake againſt the things ſpoken by Paul, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting and railing on them.</hi> And ſuch were thoſe bidden gueſts that were invited to the Wedding, that made light of it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.4, 5. Well then, there was both an attention of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:133432:27"/>the ear, and an intention of the mind and heart in this hearing of <hi>Lydia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this being the ſenſe, it offers us theſe three Concluſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D.</hi> 1. That the preaching of the Word is the ordinary means of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D.</hi> 2. That a ſerious firm and fixt applying our hearts and minds to the Word of God is required by God of them that hear it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D.</hi> 3. That ſuch an attention can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be given to the Word preached but by a ſpecial work of Grace. <hi>Lydia</hi> might have heard <hi>Paul</hi> preach, but ſhe had never heard them if God had not firſt opened her heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D.</hi> 1. That the preaching of the Word is the ordinary means of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Souls. 'Tis true the power of God is unlimited, and not bound to means; God could have taught the Eunuch without <hi>Philip,</hi> he could have conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Paul</hi> without <hi>Ananias,</hi> inſtructed <hi>Cornelius</hi> without <hi>Peter,</hi> and have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened <hi>Lydia</hi>'s heart without <hi>Paul.</hi> But the Miniſtry of the Word is that means
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:133432:28"/>which the wiſdom of God hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and ſanctified for this great work. This is the ſum of the Apoſtles Climax, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14. <hi>How ſhall they call on him on whom they have not believed? and how ſhall they believe on him of whom they have not heard, and how ſhall they hear without a Preacher?</hi> And at laſt determines the Queſtion with this concluſion, <hi>That faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To prevent any curious queſtions, why 'tis this: The Apoſtle reſolved all into the good pleaſure of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21. <hi>For ſeeing the world by wiſdom knew not God, it pleaſed God by the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs of preaching to ſave them that do believe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> But ſome may wonder how ſo weak a means ſhould work ſo great ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All is from the Spirit of Chriſt; for 'tis the office of Chriſt not only to open the will of his Father, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal the myſteries of Salvation (which he doth by his Prophetical Office) but
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:133432:28"/>alſo to be preſent when the Word is preached, and by his Spirit to teach the heart inwardly what it is taught outwardly by the Word. And now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he exerciſes his Kingly Office in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his enemies become his ſubjects; here he lays us at his feet, whileſt his Word like a ſword pierces our hearts, making us throw down our arms, thoſe weapons of ſin wherewith we have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed him; here Chriſt gets a glorious, and yet an eaſie conqueſt; for againſt his power there is none ſtands. <hi>Aſſoon as they hear they ſhall obey,</hi> Pſal. 18.44. Now that the efficacy of the Word de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on the operation of the Spirit is evident from <hi>Act.</hi> 2. before thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts were pricked at the heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we read that the Spirit fell on them like a mighty ruſhing wind, <hi>v.</hi> 2. ceaſe then to wonder when we ſee ſuch mighty effects wrought by the Goſpel, ſith 'tis not we that ſpeak but the Spirit of our Father which ſpeaketh in us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Wo then to all oppoſers and contemners of Preaching and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:133432:29"/>Alas who are thoſe that are now accounted the troublers of Iſrael but ſuch as are guilty of <hi>Elijah</hi>'s crime, that indeed are zealous for the <hi>Lord God of hoſt, &amp;c.</hi> who deny themſelves to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that torrent of ſin and corruption that like another deluge is like to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run the Nation, and for this they muſt be fed with <hi>Michajah</hi>'s hard Commons even with bread and water of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Another generation of prophane and profligate Profeſſors ſwarm every where in the World, who nauſeate this Heavenly Manna, and contemn ſound Doctrine, becauſe 'tis common. Ah we live in a Goſpel-glutted-Age where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wickedneſs and wantonneſs are the beſt requital wherewith we requite the Lord for his choiceſt Mercies. Thus with <hi>Jeſhurun</hi> we are grown fat and kick.</p>
            <p>Oh that a people ſo choicely taught and inſtructed from Heaven ſhould at laſt ſcorn the counſels of their Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father! That our Religion ſhould be loſt in Atheiſm, and that the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:133432:29"/>of Chriſt crucified ſhould become a reproach among us. There is one Scripture that I would faſten on your thoughts to prevent this ſin in ſome, which deſerves to be repented in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.2, 3. If the Word ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by Angels was ſtedfaſt and every Tranſgreſſion deſerved a juſt recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of reward, how ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great Salvation? Our guilt and ingratitude increaſeth with our injoymeats: view the compariſon in a few particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We have a more excellent Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry than they under the Law, Angels were Miniſters of the Law, but Chriſt of the Goſpel; now the threatnings of Angels, if deſpiſed, were ſeverely puniſhed; and ſhall not the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the Son of God? <hi>For that God who in former Ages ſpake unto us by his Prophets, hath in theſe laſt times ſpoken to us by his own Son,</hi> Heb. 1.2. Well, let us hear Chriſt arguing himſelf from this very Topick. <hi>The Queen of the South ſhall riſe in judgment againſt the men of this generation, for ſhe came
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:133432:30"/>from the uttermoſt parts of the earth, to hear the wiſdom of</hi> Solomon, <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a greater than</hi> Solomon <hi>is here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again, <hi>the men of</hi> Nineveh <hi>ſhall riſe in judgment,</hi> &amp;c. Mat. 12.41, 42. Oh what will be our caſe, who ſet not ſo high a price on Chriſt as that Queen did on <hi>Solomon!</hi> when Chriſt and his Goſpel come home to our door and beg entertainment: 'Tis the Language of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. <hi>We pray you in Chriſts ſtead that you be reconciled to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The very matter of preaching ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels that which was of old, for ſuch myſteries are revealed by the Goſpel, as in other Ages were not known, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.5. The Law made nothing perfect but the bringing in a better hope did, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.7. in this reſpect the Goſpel is rather called Salvation than the Law; <hi>How ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great ſalvation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The manner of revealing the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is far more clear and effectual, the Types, Propheſies, and Promiſes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, were dark and obſcure;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:133432:30"/>now <hi>Moſes</hi> face is unveiled, and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by Chriſt clearly revealed; ſo that a clearer Manifeſtation can never be expected while the World laſts. Thoſe dark and enigmatical <hi>Mediums</hi> thorow which the <hi>Jews</hi> looked to ſee a Saviour, are now taken away, and <hi>we behold as in a glaſs the glory of God</hi> &amp;c. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18, 19.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Ratification of the Goſpel was ſtronger: Their's indeed was Thunder and Lightning, Burning and Blackneſs, with other great ſigns to confirm it's Authority, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.19. But yet the Goſpel was confirmed by more and greater miracles. One inſtance ſhall be inſtead of many, for never was there any that reſtored ſight to the blind (at leaſt by his own Power,) but only Chriſt: ſee the Teſtimony of the blind man cured, <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.32. <hi>Since the World began was it not heard, that any one opened the eye of one that was born blind.</hi> Nay, Chriſt cured Souls as well as Bodies; this is evident by that graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pardon which he gave to him that was cured of the Palſy, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.2. <hi>Be
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:133432:31"/>of good cheer, thy ſins be forgiven thee:</hi> Oh yet that that Chriſt whom we preach ſhould be a ſtone of ſtumbling and a rock of Offence to diſobedient and unbelieving ones! who yet to them which believe is the only Foundation, that rock of Ages, the wiſdom of God and the Power of God! how many have their faces tanned and ſullied only under the bright beams of the Sun of Righteouſneſs; who was given as to <hi>enlighten every one that comes into the World?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, let us all learn our duty, which we ſhall comprize in theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To prize the Word preached, and acknowledg it to be that <hi>Manna</hi> upon which God intends to keep us, while (with <hi>Iſrael</hi>) we are in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs till we come to that Celeſtial <hi>Canaan.</hi> We read in <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13, &amp;c. <hi>He when he aſcended, gave ſome to be Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors, and Teachers;</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For the repairing of the Saints, for the Work of the Miniſtry,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:133432:31"/>till we all meet in a perfect man,</hi> &amp;c. Two circumſtances are here eſpecially conſiderable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When Chriſt gave us this divine gift of preaching the Goſpel: 'Twas <hi>when he aſcended to Heaven,</hi> as Kings when they are crowned give rich gifts to their favourites; So did Chriſt, when he was crowned in Heaven, he gave this rich invaluable gift to the Sons of men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us conſider why he gave it, 'twas for the <hi>repairing of the Saints;</hi> The Goſpel was never intended to ſave all, but the Saints only: <hi>As many as were ordained to eternal life, believed.</hi> Now even the Saints have their Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ruines and decays; their minds are clouded with darkneſs; their Wills are crooked, and their Affections unſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Theſe are the ruines which God repairs by the Goſpel, when he renews us by Grace, and reſtores his own Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in us; ſubmit we then to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the great God of Heaven. Though God create man at firſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of Angels, yet he doth
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:133432:32"/>not recreate or renew his Image in us, without the Miniſtry of men, <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18. we read <hi>Paul</hi> was ſent by preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to open blind eyes, <hi>that they might turn from darkneſs unto light, and from the Power of Satan unto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Improve the preaching of the Goſpel; and know that as the body cannot live without Bread, no more can the Soul without the Word; obey it in all things, as well it's precepts as it's promiſes: 'twas given to be a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory to our lives, a light to our minds, life to our Souls. Oh buy the truth and never ſell it, ſtudy to be caſt into a Goſpel-mould! Oh that the Word preached to you might be a Word implanted in you! that we could ſay of you all, as <hi>Paul</hi> of his <hi>Romans, So we preach and ſo you believe.</hi> This would fill our hearts with comfort, and make us confeſs as he of his <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; Though we preach the Goſpel in much affliction, yet with much joy.</hi> O give us a ſhare in his glorying, that we may ſay, <hi>Thanks be to God that you were once the Servants of ſin, but you
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:133432:32"/>have obeyed from the heart that form of doctrine that was delivered to you.</hi> But we come to the next Concluſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. That a ſerious firm and fixt applying our hearts and minds to the Word preached, is required by God of all that hear it; or ſhorter, thus, 'Tis the attention of the heart to the Word of God that is only ſaving. This is that duty which is ſo often preſt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcated in the Scripture, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.6. <hi>And theſe words which I command thee this day, ſhall be in thy heart;</hi> and again, Deut. 32.46. <hi>Set your hearts to all the Words which I teſtifie againſt you, ſet your hearts;</hi> that is ſaith A Lap. <hi>mentem apponite et attendite, apply your heart and hear,</hi> &amp;c. bodily Service is but the body of our Service, 'tis the Service of the Soul, that is the Soul of our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. This was <hi>Lydia's</hi> attention, which hath made her name ſmell like a ſweet perfume in Scripture, a rare compound which conſiſts of theſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ingredients.</p>
            <p n="1">1 .This ſaving attention to the Word implies a ſerious conſideration of the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:133432:33"/>things ſpoken, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.7. Conſider what I ſay, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'Tis a rule, <hi>litterae Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipum ter legendae:</hi> Kings letters ought to be read threetimes-over. Gods Meſſages muſt not be ſlighted, for his Word is no vain Word, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny did by the Angels Meſſages. 'Tis ſaid, having heard the Meſſages, <hi>ſhe pondered all theſe things in her heart,</hi> &amp;c. So ſhould we, Gods Word muſt not be born and dy the ſame hour; no, it muſt be a living and an abiding Word: God ſpake once, but the Pſalmiſt heard it twice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67.11. <hi>Phyſick</hi> can never work, nor meat nouriſh unleſs it abides ſomtime in the body, nor can the Word which is both meat and medicine to our Souls.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The next thing required to this ſaving attention is a right underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Word: theſe two Chriſt joins together, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.10. <hi>hear and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</hi> 'Tis the mind and meaning of God that we muſt chiefly attend; Chriſts own diſciples oftimes took offence at his Words, when upon better infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation they found them to be Words
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:133432:33"/>of truth and life. This was the ſad effect of that precious doctrine, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.53. <hi>Except ye eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drinks his blood, you have no life in you.</hi> Carnal reaſon knew not how to underſtand this Myſterie, and therefore preſently ſuggeſts this incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous queſtion, <hi>how can this man give us his fleſh to eat:</hi> and what a ſad effect followed on this miſtake, we read <hi>v.</hi> 66. <hi>From that time, many of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples went back, and walked no more with Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. There muſt be a faithful retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or remembrance of it; our memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are falſe and ſlippery like hour-glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, no ſooner filled at one end, but they run out at the other; riven, and chinky veſſels that leake out the Water of life, ſtrive we all we can to make them Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuries of Divine Truth, and lay up the Word of God in them as in a ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe: <hi>Thy word have I hid in my heart,</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>that I might not ſin againſt thee.</hi> To promote this Work we ſhould do as a man that hath hid a treaſure, he goes often and ſees whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:133432:34"/>it be ſafe; ſo ſhould we often turn in upon our memories, and ask them as Chriſt the diſciples, <hi>do you not remember the five Loaves,</hi> &amp;c. and the rather becauſe we have a dangerous and ſubtile enemy, who watches where we keep our treaſures, and unleſs we watch it narrowly will ſteal it from us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We muſt entertain it with love, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Becauſe they received not the truth in the Love thereof, therefore God ſhall give them up to ſuffer ſtrong deluſions;</hi> want of Love to the Word is the firſt ſtep to Apoſtacy. See a Soul ſeaſoned with this Grace of Love, in <hi>Jeremy, Chap.</hi> 15.16. <hi>Thy words were found and I did eat them, and they were unto me the joy and rejoycing of my heart.</hi> God makes his appear to the Conſcience of the experienced Chriſtian, <hi>Mic.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Are not my words good to him that walketh uprightly?</hi> Yes Lord, ſo good that the Soul that taſtes and digeſts them, confeſſes they are <hi>ſweeter than hony or the hony-comb.</hi> If the myſteries of the Goſpel are ſo
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:133432:34"/>ſweet and ſacred, that the Angels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves deſire to pry into them, how dearly then ſhould duſt and aſhes love them! Oh that we could ſay as the <hi>Pſalmiſt; How do I love thy Law? all the day long is my ſtudy in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The Word muſt be heard with Faith; every hearer is not a profitable hearer. As hearing diſtinguiſhes Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours from the Profane, ſo believing diſtinguiſheth the upright from hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.2. <hi>The word preached did not profit them that heard it, becauſe it was not mixt with faith:</hi> and again, <hi>'Tis the Power of God to ſalvation, but to them that do believe, Rom.</hi> 1.16. Though it be true, that without the Word there can be no Faith, (<hi>for Faith cometh by hearing</hi>); yet withal with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Faith the Word hath no power. As the Braſen Serpent was of no uſe to them that did not look on it; ſo 'tis in this caſe, <hi>Look therefore unto me and be you ſaved:</hi> when we come to hear, we ſhould all think that we hear God ſpeaking to us as he did to <hi>Ezekiel, Son of man eat that thou findeſt, Ezek.</hi> 3.1.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:133432:35"/>Faith is the life of the Soul: As there heat in a dead-mans mouth never doth good, no more doth the Word in a faithleſs hearer. 'Tis Faith that makes every part thereof powerful and effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ual, its precepts to direct us, its threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings to terrifie us, its promiſes to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort us. Take but one inſtance in <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah,</hi> 3.5. we read that the men of <hi>Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh believed God,</hi> (1) upon hearing <hi>Jonah</hi> his ſermon, <hi>and then they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed a faſt and put on ſackcloth.</hi> Faith is that living womb into which when the ſeed of the Word falls, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a fruitful mother of all ſpiritual Graces.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Laſtly, to a ſaving attention there is required a univerſal obedience, and a hearty reſignation of our ſelves. This was the Apoſtles Crown and Joy, that his <hi>Romans</hi> had <hi>obeyed from the heart that form of doctrine that they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,</hi> Rom. 6.17. and this is Gods end in giving you his Word, that it ſhould <hi>bring every thought into the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.5. We ſhould take heed of hearing with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:133432:35"/>ears and ſtubborn hearts. The ſence of Gods mercy in revealing his Will, and the Conſcience of our duty to obey it, ſhould make us ſo ready to every thing that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, that a little child ſhould lead us, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Hence firſt is condemned that viſible liſtleſsneſs and ſupine negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence that many diſcover in this duty of hearing. Can we chuſe but trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to hear that curſe that is threatned againſt every one that doth Gods work negligently, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48.10. and yet alas, how many of us hear as if we did not hear, and mind no more the word of life, than if we were hearing art Idle tale! The Church hath ever been peſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered with ſuch profeſſors. God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.32. <hi>Son of man, this People come and ſit before thee, as my People uſe to do,</hi> &amp;c. Oh hear once more and tremble at that dreadful ſentence which Chriſt breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt incredulous and refractory hearers, in <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.48. <hi>He that refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth me and heareth not my words, hath
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:133432:36"/>one that judgeth, even the word that I have ſpoken, the ſame ſhall judg him.</hi> Sure it will be a double damnation to be condemned by the Goſpel, yet thus it will be, if it be not <hi>the ſaviour of life to life,</hi> it will be <hi>the Saviour of death to death.</hi> And what greater equity than this do not ſuch judg themſelves unworthy everlaſting life, that leave their hearts behind them when they come to hear it? doth not that malefactor deſerve to dye, when his pardon is ſent him freely, that has it read as if he were a-ſleep? Theſe meſſengers that were ſent by <hi>Benhadad</hi> to make peace with <hi>Ahab</hi> (when diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſed by him) will riſe in judgment againſt ſuch drouſy hearers. We read the men took diligent heed if they could catch any word of him that they might take hold of for their hope; and they did ſo, for when they arreſted him thus; <hi>Thy ſervant Benhadad ſaith, I pray thee let me live, the King of Iſrael anſwered, is he yet alive? he is my brother:</hi> and they took hold of that word, and ecchoed it back to him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>thy brother Benhadad.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:133432:36"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Attend then as <hi>Lydia</hi> did, that you may be ſaved as <hi>Lydia</hi> was, whatſoever you do (ſaith the Preacher) <hi>do it with all thy might, Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10. Judg of the importance of the duty by the earneſt injunction of the great God of heaven: <hi>ſettle it in your hearts, Luk.</hi> 21.14. and why? for the water of life will run out or run beſides us, if we do not hear with a holy heedful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Wherefore we ought to give diligent heed to the things which we have heard, leſt at any time we let them ſlip.</hi> The Greek Word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies either to run beſides, as water that flows beſides a place; or elſe it ſignifies to run thorough a thing as water thorow a ſieve: well, the word preached, if it be not heedfully heard will never ſtay in us, but be loſt and run out. This is damage ſufficient, a loſs that is irreparable, none indeed like this loſs when we receive the Grace of God in vain. For directions I ſhall refer you to what hath bin already ſaid, a word or two by way of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:133432:37"/>
            <p n="1">1. To incourage us to this heedful hearing of the Word, conſider that it is a complexive duty, a duty which is ſo acceptable to God, that under it are comprehended all duties of Religion, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3. <hi>Hear and your Souls ſhall live,</hi> life and death enter in the ſame way: As death entered into the world by the ear, by our firſt Parents liſtning to that old Manſlaier; ſo God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that life ſhould enter by the ſame door: <hi>The dead ſhall hear the voice of the ſon of God, and they that hear ſhall live, Joh.</hi> 5.25. Oh you that love heaven, love hearing too!</p>
            <p n="2">2. The moſt eminent Saints of God have ever bin obſerved to be the moſt diligent and attentive hearers, <hi>Luk</hi> 4.20. <hi>We read while Chriſt Jeſus war preaching, the eyes of all his hearers were faſtned on him;</hi> a good way, not only to prevent diſtractions but alſo to raiſe our affections; our hearts are wily, and will give us the ſlip. It is our wiſdom by all ways imaginable to ingage our hearts in hearing, and lay bonds upon them to hold them to ſuch
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:133432:37"/>an attention as becomes us. 'Tis ſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of <hi>Englands</hi> ſecond <hi>Joſiah,</hi> that peer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Prince <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, that he uſually ſtood at ſermon and took notice all the while he was a-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider, that we never read of more bitter complaints from God, than when he complained of heartleſs hearers in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.13. <hi>O that my People would have hearkned to me,</hi> &amp;c. but my People would not hear my voice, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> would none of me; and in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.10. <hi>Forty years long was I grieved with this generation and ſaid; It is a People that err in heart, for they have not known my ways:</hi> they knew, but not practically, their ears were uncircumciſed, and their hearts unſanctified. <hi>O fearful judgment to have ears that we ſhould not hear,</hi> &amp;c. Thus God puniſhes one ſin with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Rom,</hi> 11.8. who can read with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out aſtoniſhment, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. from the 13. <hi>v.</hi> to the 17. <hi>I aroſe up early and ſpake unto you, but you would not hear, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will do unto you as unto</hi> Shilo, &amp;c.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:133432:38"/>Read it thorow, I forbear the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, deſiring if ever you remember<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a leſſon, you would remember this, and never give your Teachers cauſe to complain. Oh we have laboured in vain, and ſpent our ſtrength for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing!</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, To cloſe all carry with you St. <hi>James</hi> caution, be not forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hearers of the Word, but doers alſo: he hears aright (ſaith one) that doth not contradict his hearing by his life; otherwiſe you will be as a man that ſees his face in a glaſs and turns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and forgets what manner of man he was. O waſh off thoſe ſpots which this glaſs diſcovers! ſo hear the Word of Chriſt, that you may conform to the will of Chriſt, <hi>Lydia's</hi> attention was the firſt ſtep to Salvation. Hear as ſhe did, and you will be happy as ſhe was.</p>
            <p>So much Briefly of this Work of Grace which God wrought in open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the heart of <hi>Lydia.</hi> Reader, let me carry thee one ſtep farther, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:133432:38"/>ſhew thee Gods end in this Work, or why he thus opens the heart. And that is, that himſelf may enter, and dwell in it, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. <hi>That Chriſt may dwell in your hearts.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:133432:39"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Epheſ. 3.17. the former part of the Verſe.</bibl> 
                  <hi>That Chriſt may dwell in your hearts by faith.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe words are part of a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous prayer which the Apoſtle puts up to God in the behalf of his dear <hi>Epheſians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The prayer begins in the 14th. <hi>ver.</hi> where we find <hi>Paul</hi> upon his knees, begging Grace for them of the Father of Mercies: <hi>For this cauſe I bow my knees to the Father of mercies, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The bleſſings that he begs for them, are eſpecially two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He begs the gift of ſpiritual ſtrength, that as they had begun well, and laid a good foundation by belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in Chriſt, ſo they might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in holding out that profeſſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the enemies and oppoſitions which they met with, and were like to turn them out of the way of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Thus he prays <hi>ver.</hi> the 16. <hi>That
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:133432:39"/>he would give you according to the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his glory, to be ſtrengthened with might by the ſpirit in the inner man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe that are wholly under the power of corruption are not ſo much troubled with perſecution and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Satan like a Pyrate ſeldom ſets upon a ſoul unleſs like a Ship it be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with the merchandiſe of Grace. This was the caſe with theſe <hi>Epheſians.</hi> By <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching they had begun well, building on that rock of Ages, and venturing their Immortal Souls on Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs. But <hi>Paul</hi> now being in priſon, falſe Teachers were among them, vexing the Church, and were like to turn them from the way of truth: God had ſmitten the ſhepherd, and the ſheep were like to be ſcattered. Now then is a time to preſs the duty of perſeverance, that as they had begun well, ſo they might ſo run that they might obtain.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He begs that ſoveraign means that was only able to confirm and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them in the Service of Chriſt, and that is Chriſt himſelf. That Chriſt may
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:133432:40"/>dwell in your hearts by Faith.</p>
            <p>I ſhall a little explain the words:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Chriſt,</hi> that is, whole Chriſt in both his natures, God and Man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May dwell,</hi> that is, ſpiritually poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs, live and work.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In your hearts,</hi> that is, in the inner man, conſiſting of the Underſtanding, Will and Affections, which are the principal and chief place of Chriſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence, the fort Royal, or Caſtle which Chriſt chuſeth, and above all delights in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By faith,</hi> that is, as the means and inſtrument whereby we receive and entertain him</p>
            <p>There are as many Doctrines offer themſelves to us as there are words in this Scripture. And we might note firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. That the heart is the place of Chriſts reſidence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. Chriſt is no ſtranger to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, but an in-dweller with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 3. That Faith makes a union between Chriſt and the Soul.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall wave prolixity, and bring
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:133432:40"/>my Diſcourſe into a narrower model, caſting all into this one Concluſion.</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>That no bleſſing whatſoever (on this ſide heaven) can be imagined, that we ſhould more deſire than this;</hi> That Chriſt ſhould dwell in our hearts by Faith.</p>
            <p>We find the Apoſtles affections all in a flame, and he burns with zeal to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the happineſs of his dear <hi>Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> he bends his knees, and caſts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf down at Gods feet, and among all bleſſings in Heaven and Earth, he can find none better to beg for his young Converts than this.</p>
            <p>What the ſtrength of his affections was to them you may ſee <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.16. where we read, that <hi>he ceaſed not to give thanks for them, making mention of them always in his prayers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had <hi>Paul</hi> known any bleſſing better than this, ſure he whoſe heart was ſo ſet upon them, would have begged it for them.</p>
            <p>But further, to prove the greatneſs of this ineſtimable bleſſing, read 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. where the Apoſtle enjoyns his
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:133432:41"/>
               <hi>Corinthians</hi> the higheſt pitch of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon this ground: <hi>For what agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath the temple of God with idols? for ye are the temple of the living God; as he hath ſaid, I will dwell in them, and walk among them, and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Scripture we have a double argument to prove the greatneſs of this bleſſing, (1) Chriſts dwelling in his people.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The greatneſs of the duty that is urged from it, <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>Come forth from among them, and be ye ſeparate, &amp;c.</hi> Now for weighty ſervices, God uſually furniſhes his people with ſtrongeſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments; as is evident in <hi>Abraham's</hi> caſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. 'twas high ſervice that God enjoyned him, <hi>Walk, before me, and be thou perfect.</hi> And high encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements God gave him, <hi>I am God all-ſufficient,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Deus jubet &amp; juvat;</hi> God's Commands carry ſtrength with them, whatever <hi>Abraham</hi>'s weakneſs be; yet this ſupports him, that the everlaſting arms are under him, God is all-ſufficient both for the work and reward.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:133432:41"/>
            <p>'Twas hard work too on which God ſet <hi>Moſes</hi> when he ſent him with a commiſſion to deliver <hi>Iſrael</hi> from <hi>Egypt,</hi> and ſuitable encouragements God gives him; God finds his heart low, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it to a height ſuiting his ſervice, by working no leſs than three ſeveral Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles to ſtrengthen him; his Rod is turned into a Serpent, his hand is le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous; and the river is turned into blood, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond argument which this Scripture yields us to prove the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this bleſſing is this, That Chriſts dwelling in us is but a ſhort abridgment of the Covenant of Grace, for that's preſently added, <hi>I will be your God, and you ſhall be my people.</hi> When we have ſummed up all thoſe invaluable bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings that are treaſured up in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, we have all in a little, (<hi>viz.</hi>) in Chriſt dwelling in us, peace, pardon, grace, glory, all is virtually compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2ly.</hi> Again, 'tis the very bleſſing God promiſes the Saints in Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.3. where S. <hi>John</hi> ſaw the new Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:133432:42"/>coming down from God out of Heaven, <hi>&amp;c. He heard a voice from heaven, ſaying, Behold the Tabernacle of God is with men, and he will dwell with them, and they ſhall be his people, &amp;c.</hi> Chriſts dwelling in us is but Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven aforehand, or Heaven upon Earth; if God dwell in us here by his Grace, he will dwell with us in glory.</p>
            <p>But for our more Methodical proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the point, I ſhall confine my ſelf to this method.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. I ſhall explain it.</item>
               <item>2. Confirm; and,</item>
               <item>3. Apply it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>For the Explication, I ſhall do that by anſwering ſeveral Queries in which the ſum of the Concluſion lies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 1. The firſt is what we are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by the heart?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not to trouble our ſelves with the various acceptations of the word [<hi>heart</hi>] in Scripture, (many of which are impertinent to our purpoſe) we are to underſtand (by heart) the Will and the Affections eſpecially, as in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Diſcourſe; theſe are the ſpring
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:133432:42"/>out of which are the iſſues of life, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.22. and that good treaſure mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.24. <hi>But a good man out of the good treaſure of his heart, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> The next thing to be enquired, is, what we are to underſtand by Chriſts dwelling in us?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It's a Metaphorical or figurative ſpeech, to ſhew that intimacy and holy acquaintance that is between Chriſt and Believers, Chriſt is not in the heart as a ſtranger in an Inn, where he tarries but a night, but as a man dwelling in his own houſe where he lives, and works, and rules, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> More particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, this dwelling of Chriſt implys theſe ſeveral things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It implys propriety, Chriſt will never uſurp where he hath no right; no, he never dwells but in his own; his own he will never loſe, and more than his own he will never take; <hi>All that the Father hath given me ſhall come to me,</hi> Job. 6.37. Satan ſhall never ſit quiet for ever in a ſoul that belongs to Chriſt; though the ſtrong man armed keeps the houſe, yet a ſtronger than
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:133432:43"/>himſelf will come and bind him, not one of thoſe that are heirs of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſhall miſcarry; no, <hi>I will ranſom them from the Power of the grave, I will redeem them from death,</hi> Hoſ. 13.14.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Chriſt's dwelling in believers im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies actual poſſeſſion, a man may have a juſt right or claim where yet he may not dwell; Chriſt doth not content himſelf with a bare right to his redeemed, but he takes actual poſſeſſion of them; he keeps houſe in theirs hearts, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.20. <hi>At that day, you ſhall know that I am in my Father, and you in me and I in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Furthermore Chriſt Jeſus may be ſaid to poſſeſs believers two ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By aſſuming our nature, <hi>When the Word was made fleſh, he dwelt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, Joh.</hi> 1.14. (1) lived and converſed awhile with the ſons of men; yea he dwelt in us in as much as he was partaker of fleſh and blood with us. And as the fulneſs of the God-head dwelt in Chriſt, ſo Chriſt too dwells in us.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:133432:43"/>
            <p n="2">2. By communicating to us his Spirit. The Spirit of Chriſt is the Fountain of all Grace and comfort, and by this Spirit of Chriſt we have both union and communion with him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Chriſt liveth in me,</hi> Chriſt is in us as a Principle of life and Grace, active and operative; he is not in the Soul as once he was in the ſhip aſleep, but always inciting, quickening and enlivening his elect who would again becom dead in ſin, but he acts and excites his own Grace in them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſts dwelling in us, means the neereſt intimacy that is imaginable; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo 'tis in the original, I will indwell in them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. As if Chriſt could never have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion enough with his People. Now this ſweet and ſaving intimacy will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in thoſe things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His People ſhall know his ſecrets, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.14. <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him, and he will ſhew them his Covenant.</hi> The ſaints are all Gods ſecretaries; when God intended that fearful overthrow of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:133432:44"/>
               <hi>Sodom,</hi> ſhall I hide from <hi>Abraham</hi> (ſaies God) the thing that I do? No, <hi>Abraham</hi> was his friend, and as a boſom-friend; He ſhall know his Councell, ſuch honour have all his ſaints.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He will ſpeak to their hearts, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.14. When the hearts of Gods People are ſo overwhelmed with grief; that men and Angels prove miſerable comforters. They may ſpeak to the ear but cannot reach the heart; then Chriſt alone doth this; <hi>I, even I, am he that doth comfort thee,</hi> &amp;c. Iſa. 51.12. Chriſt ſpeaks ſuch things as make our hearts leap. Thus he ſpake to the ſick-man, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.2. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on be of good cheer; thy ſins be forgiven thee.</hi> Chriſt can ſpeak ſuch Words as never man ſpake, the Words which he ſpeaks are Spirit and life. 'Tis ſtoried of a Peer of this Kingdom that he dyed with joy of an unexpected pardon; how great then is the joy that poſſeſſeth a Soul that receives a pardon from God! Such pardoned ones are bid to be glad and ſhout for joy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.11. And all others flatly forbid to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:133432:44"/>with this joy, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9.1. <hi>Rejoyce not,</hi> O Iſrael, <hi>for joy as other People, for thou haſt gone a-whoring from thy God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſweetneſs and cloſneſs of that intimacy which we have with Chriſt, by vertue of his dwelling in us, appears by this, that we have all things common with Chriſt. Chriſt calls nothing his own that may do us good: all lour freſh Springs are in him, if we are Chriſts, all is ours, <hi>Paul, Apollo, Cephas,</hi> life and death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All Chriſt's offices and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacies, his life, death, blood, merit, Spirit; all his advantage to us, yea death it ſelf is gain to believers, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21. <hi>For me to live is Chriſt, and to dye is gain.</hi> The Church keeps all her choice preſents for Chriſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 7. <hi>vlt.</hi> And Chriſt beſtows all his rarities on his Church.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſt dwelling in us implies his abiding or continual reſiding in us, in <hi>Iſa.</hi> the 57.15. God is ſaid to inhabit eternity, (1) who only is eternal; wherever Chriſt dwells he takes up his reſidence for ever; he ſaith, this
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:133432:45"/>is my reſt for ever, here will I dwell <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Though men may be weary of their dwelling how-ever accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted both for neceſſity and delight; yet Chriſt is never: That's the promiſe he makes his People, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 6.13. <hi>I will dwell among the children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and will not forſake my People</hi> Iſrael.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Chriſts dwelling in us implies his preſervation of us, every man is bound to repair and preſerve his own houſe where he dwells, ſo is Chriſt: Chriſt's dwelling doth not look like the houſe of the ſluggard that drops thorow; no, what-ever ſtorms beat on it it ſtands, and is impregnable. That's remarkable in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.7.2.3. <hi>At</hi> Salem <hi>is his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, and his dwelling at</hi> Sion; <hi>There brake he the arrows of the bow,</hi> &amp;c. That place is ſure of ſafetie and protection where God dwells; as on the contrary, Gods departing makes way for deſtruction. We read that the Heathens have placed their Security in the preſence of their idol-Gods. <hi>Tacitus</hi> reports of the <hi>Tyrians,</hi> when they were beſieged by <hi>Alexander,</hi> bound
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:133432:45"/>
               <hi>Hercules</hi> with a golden chain that he ſhould not depart. And the <hi>Romans</hi> were wont by ſome verſes to call off the Tutelary gods out of the Cities which they did beſiege. God hath bound himſelf to us by a Covenant better than a golden chain, that he will never leave us nor forſake us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> 3. The third Query is how Chriſt dwells in the heart by faith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The anſwer is this, 'Tis the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Faith to receive Chriſt Jeſus. Chriſt knocks by his Word and Spirit, and Faith makes haſte to open and let him in; it gives Chriſt the free and full poſſeſſion of the Soul, and delivers up all into his hand, and to his uſe. For can two walk together unleſs they are agreed? We read in <hi>Gen.</hi> 30.6. <hi>When Lot and Abraham had multiplied their ſubſtance, they could not dwell together, and there was ſtrife between their herds<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;</hi> Chriſt and we could never have dwelt together; had there been any ſtrife between us; there is no agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment between Chriſt and Belial. But when Chriſt comes and dwells in us,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:133432:46"/>he comes like <hi>Noah</hi>'s Dove, he brings us news of peace purchaſed by the blood of his Croſs. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mires the happineſs of ſuch as dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in unity, though but natural brethren, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133.1. <hi>Behold how good and pleaſant a thing it is, &amp;c.</hi> How good then and pleaſant muſt it be for Chriſt and us to dwell together! This is our happineſs, Chriſt ſays of every believing ſoul as of Sion, <hi>This is my reſt for ever, here will I dwell, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal.132.14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſ.</hi> 2. Such in whom Chriſt dwells, ſhall never loſe their intereſt in God by ſin or backſliding, for Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf will be a continual ſpring or foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of life and grace within us, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.14. <hi>The water that I ſhall give you ſhall be in you a well of living water.</hi> Can we ever die with thirſt when we have a fountain within us? no fear of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting our title to that great and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious inheritance if Chriſt be in us, he will keep both it for us, and us for it, <hi>he will preſerve us by his grace unto his heavenly Kingdom,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.18.</p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:133432:46"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſ.</hi> 3. If Chriſt dwell in us, he will defend and protect us from all dangers; death and hell have nothing to do where Chriſt the Lord of life dwells. When <hi>Lazarus</hi> was dead, his ſiſter told Chriſt, <hi>Lord, if thou hadſt been here my brother had not died,</hi> Joh. 11.21. Chriſts preſence is his peoples ſecurity from hat ſecond death. Satan may bring up his black Legions, and ſtorm the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, but ſhall never take it. Hear ye whoſe hearts are habitations for the Lord Chriſt what your Redeemer ſaith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.30. <hi>The Prince of this world cometh and hath nothing in me,</hi> (that is) in me myſtical, neither id head nor members.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſ.</hi> 4. If Chriſt dwell in us, we ſhall never want either counſel or comfort, his Spirit ſhall ſupply us with both. If we want counſel we ſhall hear a voice behind us, ſaying, <hi>this is the way walk in it.</hi> He whoſe name is <hi>Counſellor,</hi> hath not his name for nothing; in our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt perplexities, this great Counſellor will adviſe and direct us, for he is made of God to be wiſdom to his redeemed.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:133432:47"/>Again, if we want comfort, he'l revive the drooping ſpirits of his contrite ones, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. The Church out of her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience cries but, <hi>that his mouth is as ſweet things,</hi> Cant. 5.16. And the words that he ſpeaks are as life to deſpondent and dying ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 5. But one thing more: Chriſt will never leave his dwelling till he bring us to a dwelling-place with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in glory. This was purchaſed to us by his death, and prepared for us by his Aſcenſion, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.2. <hi>I go to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare a place for you.</hi> No ſooner ſhall theſe earthly houſes be diſſolved, but Chriſt is preſently ready to receive us into everlaſting habitations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. The Application follows, and let the firſt Uſe be of Information. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. It diſcovers the vain deluſion of all hypocrites and formaliſts, who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Chriſt into their mouths, but ſhut him out of their hearts; this was the Religion of the Phariſees, whoſe falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in matters of Gods Worſhip, Chriſt Jeſus reprehends, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.8. <hi>Well did Iſaias propheſie of you, ſaying, this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:133432:47"/>draweth nigh unto me with their mouth, and honoureth me with their lips, but have removed their hearts far from me.</hi> 'Tis ſad when Chriſt is neer in our mouths, but far from our reins.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Learn hence next, That there is nothing loſt by giving Chriſt entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. No, 'tis the gain of a Chriſtian; as God bleſſed <hi>Obed-edom</hi> for enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Ark, ſo doth he much more bleſs Believers for entertaining his Son Chriſt. What glorious gueſts had juſt <hi>Lot</hi> when he entertained two Angels! a much more glorious gueſt hath every one that entertains Chriſt Jeſus; he brings Salvation with him, and ſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutes the heart that receives him as he did <hi>Zachens, This day is ſalvation come to thy houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Learn next what a myſtery, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miracle there is in the actings of ſaving Faith, in that it unites Chriſt and the ſoul, and brings them to dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Wonder we may, that though Chriſt, in regard of his humane nature be in Heaven, and we on Earth; yet Faith eaſily narrows this wide diſtance
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:133432:48"/>and in an inſtant poſſeſſes the ſoul with its beloved Jeſus. As the ſoul by vertue of ſight inlightned with the Sun, doth joyn it ſelf with the body of the Sun, and touch it (after a manner); ſo the eye of Faith inlightned with the beams of the Spirit which come from the Sun of righteouſneſs, doth joyn and unite it ſelf with Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. The next is a uſe of Trial. If it be ſo great a bleſſing to have Chriſt Jeſus dwelling in our hearts, it concerns us all to try whether he dwell in our hearts or no.</p>
            <p>Now the tokens of his preſence, or evidences of his co-habitation with us, may be theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The heart in which Chriſt dwells is an humble heart, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. Chriſt was a pattern of Humility himſelf, <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of ſpirit.</hi> And Chriſt delights to be no-where but in a heart that is like himſelf. The richer the Ship is laden, the more water it draws, and the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er it ſails; ſo 'tis here: that heart that carries Chriſt, is laden with more than
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:133432:48"/>a golden mine, it carries him in whom are hid all ſpiritual treaſures, and all ſuch ſouls ſail low. <hi>Abraham</hi> calls him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf duſt and aſhes; <hi>David,</hi> a worm and no man; great <hi>Paul,</hi> the chiefeſt of ſinners; though every Saint that is his ſucceſſor, contend ſtill for that title, The moſt hard-hearted ſinner; ſo Mr. <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> ſubſcribed his Letter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The heart where Chriſt dwells, is inflamed with the love of God. In cold frozen ſpirits, or hearts that are luke-warm like <hi>Laodicea,</hi> Chriſt likes not to be; as the Sun begets heat on in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour bodies by ſhining, on them, ſo doth Chriſt the Sun of Righteouſneſs when he ariſeth on a ſoul; though he find our hearts cold, yet he makes them by his ſpiritual preſence burn within us; as it fared with them with whom he journeyed to <hi>Emaus,</hi> Luk. 24.32. The ſoul burns with love, and burns with deſire to Chriſt Jeſus, that is once uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, Read <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.23. <hi>If any man love me he will keep my word, and my Father will love him, and we will come unto him and make our abode with him.</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:133432:49"/>As when Chriſt comes, he comes willing; ſo where he comes he comes welcome. <hi>Mary</hi> entertained Chriſt, and ſhe loved him much, and this love diſcovered it ſelf in ſpending that coſtly Oyntment on his ſacred body. There's nothing too dear for Chriſt in his account where Chriſt dwells, but ſuch a one ſays with the Martyr, He is glad he hath any thing to loſe for Chriſt; or with the Church, whatever good thing he hath, he keeps it only for him, <hi>Cant.</hi> 7.13.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly; With love to our Brethren, <hi>If we love one another, God dwelleth in us,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.12. God loves to be where love is. One obſerves, That where the Devil dwells all is in peace, much more where God dwells who is the God of peace. If then we find our hearts filled with malice and hatred to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our brethren, we may confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude God is not in this place; the Lamb of God will never lie in a Lions den. We read in <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.23. God ſent an evil ſpirit between the houſe of <hi>Abijam</hi> and the men of <hi>Shechem,</hi> a ſpirit of hatred, enmity and diviſion:
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:133432:49"/>This is an evil Spirit from the Devil, not from God; where <hi>Satan</hi> dwells he ſets all on fire, not with fire that warms, but conſumes. And when we give place to wrath we give place to the Devil, <hi>Epheſ</hi> 4.27.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The heart wherein Chriſt dwells, is a holy heart; as no unholy thing ſhall for ever dwell with him, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will Chriſt dwell with it.</p>
            <p>The heart is a Temple, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Ye are the; Temples of the holy Ghoſt;</hi> now we know Temples are holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated things: That which is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to be done in another place is not lawful to be done in a Temple: we read, <hi>Mark</hi> 11.16. Chriſt would not ſuffer a veſſel to be carried thorow the Temple. Neither will he have the hearts of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers made a rode for ſin; no, <hi>If any man defiles the Temple of God, him will God deſtroy,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.17.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The heart where Chriſt dwells lives in a ſweet ſubjection to Chriſt and his Laws. <hi>His commands are not griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but his yoke is eaſy and his burden light;</hi> Chriſt dwells no-where, but where he is acknowledged and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:133432:50"/>ſerves as a King; for God hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him both for a Prince and a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.31. The Government is laid by God upon his ſhoulders, and he makes every thought to ſtoop and come into ſubjection to himſelf. Well then, where men ſerve not the Lord but their luſts, ſet up their corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and cry down Chriſt; in ſuch hearts Chriſt never dwells. But a Soul poſſeſt by Chriſt, ſets Chriſt in the Throne, and cryes up Chriſt, as the Jews did <hi>Caeſar;</hi> We have no King but him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The heart in which Chriſt dwells is a tender heart. <hi>Such as tremble at Gods Word, Iſa.</hi> 57.15. A hard ſenſleſs heart is a dead heart. And as the Angels to the Women that ſought Chriſt in the ſepulchre; So we may ſay in this caſe, <hi>Why ſeek ye the living among the dead?;</hi> Chriſt is a Spring and a Fountain of life to every believing Soul: <hi>Becauſe I live ye ſhall live alſo.</hi> Now where there is life there is ſenſe; dead men nor fear any thing nor feel it, but living men do both; they feel the leaſt guilt, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:133432:50"/>fear the wrath and anger of God; they are ſenſible of every miſcarriage, and their heart ſmites them on the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the leaſt ſin, as <hi>David</hi> did when he cut off but the lap of <hi>Sauls,</hi> garment. Such a heart ſhews who is in it (to wit) that Chriſt dwells in't: ſuch a heart we read was in good <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,</hi> whoſe heart was ſo tender that he wept but at the reading of the Law, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. This ſhould cheer the hearts of all believers: what unſpeakable comfort doth this bring to every one whoſe heart is a habitation for Chriſt Jeſus! how doth Chriſt honour you, that when the World ſcorns you, Chriſt crowns you; when men ſhun you, the Son of God dwells in you. Surely this bleſſing affords mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Spiritual raviſhment to every Soul that has given Chriſt Jeſus enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment. Wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> admired both Gods mercy and his Peoples happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at once, upon this very reaſon, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.18. Is it true indeed that God will dwell with man on earth!
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:133432:51"/>what infinite Majeſty fall in love with miſery! God dwell with man! heaven and earth meet in one Perſon! ye righteous, let it not deject you, that your excellency is not conſpicuous in the Worlds eye. The Churches beauty is within; and herein ſhe is like her beloved. Chriſt himſelf to outward appearance was but a root out of a dry ground; no form or comelineſs was in him; therefore he was deſpiſed and rejected of men. Your life is a hidden life, like in this to the Ark, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out was covered with skins, ſullied and weather-beaten with ſtorms and tempeſts; but within, was ſtored with gold and rich rarities. God ſeeth not as man ſeeth, there's a time at hand when God will turn your in-ſide out; and though now you ly among the pots, yet ſhall ye be covered with ſilver-Wings and your feathers like gold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. Laſtly, Be exorted to the Apoſtles Prayer, to add your own practiſe. This is the one thing neceſſary, with what holy zeal and diligence
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:133432:51"/>ſhould we do this work, and drive this great deſign! how reſtleſs ſhould we be in this purſuit, to get Chriſt to dwell in us!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> But how?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I ſhall only Anſwer this query and conclude.</p>
            <p>And here ſeveral things muſt be done both for the getting Chriſt into the heart, and the keeping of him there.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The heart muſt be prepared for ChriſtW, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.1. The Prophet ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> ſaith, that he ſhould <hi>prepare the way for him.</hi> And <hi>Iſa.</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame Meſſenger adds; <hi>Every mountain ſhall he brought low, and every vally be filled up, and every crooked thing ſhall be made plain,</hi> Iſa. 43.4. All this muſt be done as a preparation for Chriſt.</p>
            <p>As where Princes are expected, the highways are cleered, and all paſſages are facilitated that they may paſs both with eaſe and honour: ſo we muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Mountains muſt be brought low; (that is) the lofty heart muſt be aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and every high thought muſt ſtoop
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:133432:52"/>and be made ſubject to the ſcepter of Chriſt: we muſt be vile in our own eyes, learn to abhor out ſelves with <hi>Job,</hi> loath our own ſins and our own righteouſneſs alſo, and count it dung and loſs to win Chriſt. Chriſt deſigns his own Glory in condeſcending to dwell with ſinful men; and Chriſt's Glory and the creature's cannot be ſet up together.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Vallies muſt be filled; ſome hearts are too low for Chriſt, they mind earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, and therefore are unfit for the receiving of ſo glorious a gueſt: <hi>Lift up therefore your heads, O ye gates, and then the King of Glory ſhall come in, Pſal.</hi> 24. as the Church is deſcribed in <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. with the moon under her feet, and then ſhe is cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Sun and hath a Crown of twelve Stars on her head; ſo muſt every member of the Church trample upon all earthly and ſublunary vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and ſet our hearts on heaven, where our true Treaſure is. It were a diſparagement to divine bleſſings, ſhould they be beſtowed on them that
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:133432:52"/>prize nothing but earthly trifles; ſuch pearls do not uſe to be caſt before ſwine.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Crooked things muſt be made ſtraight, we muſt have no crooked aimes nor cloſe deſigns in the Service of God. The ſons of <hi>Jacob</hi> muſt be all like their Father, plain-hearted men, our ſtudies, ſtrength, time, and ſtate, muſt be all dedicated to the Lord; <hi>Such as turn aſide to crooked ways,</hi> the Lord threatens to <hi>lead them out with the workers of iniquity, Pſal.</hi> 125.5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, rough ways muſt be made plain, the oyle of Grace muſt ſupple the rough and rugged temper of our Spirits. 'Tis ſaid of <hi>Nabal,</hi> he was ſo churliſh a man could not ſpeak to him; ſuch hearts are not fit for Chriſt. Chriſt by Grace ſweetens the Temper of out Souls, takes off that fierceneſs and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity that is in them by nature. <hi>The Lion and the Lamb ly down together, and there's nothing ſhall deſtroy or hurt in all his holy mountain</hi> If we would have Chriſt dwell in our hearts, we muſt keep our hearts pure;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:133432:53"/>for a naſty lodging is lothſome to him. With what care do we keep our Temples, cleanſing them continually that there be no filth found in them! Theſe Spiritual Temples muſt never be ſulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſin, nor defiled with iniquity. This is the condition upon which Chriſt promiſes to dwell in us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>Touch no unclean thing, and then I will dwell in you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Take heed of grieving the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, by reſiſting it's motions, or croſſing the ſweet and ſaving ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations thereof. There's a ſad Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.44. <hi>When the unclean Spirit is caſt out and returneth,</hi> &amp;c. He brings with him ſeven other Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits worſe than himſelf and they enter in and dwell there. Oh deal courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly with Chriſt, offend your own Souls rather than offend him! ſtudy we muſt to comply with his commands; and carry our ſelves ſo exactly, that in nothing we grieve his Spirit, nor make him weary of his habitation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, ſith Chriſt dwells in the heart by Faith, labour to prize this
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:133432:53"/>precious Grace, for the procuring of which theſe ſeveral rules ſhould</p>
            <p n="1">1. Acquaint your ſelves with your own hearts, and you will find ſuch a ſtock of infidelity in them, as may for ever confound us. Though God who is faithfulneſs it ſelf hath infinitely ſtoopt to loſt man, and for his ſecurity hath ratified the Covenant by his Word, his Oath, and Seals: <hi>yet alas there is in us all by nature a heart of unbelief,</hi> Heb. 3.12. So that upon experience we ſhall find we are no more able by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to believe the Goſpel than to obey the Law: Alas, we fear no more than we feel, and believe no more than we ſee, when we come to ſeize on Chriſt, and take hold of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, Oh with what a faint and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling hand do we receive them!</p>
            <p n="2">2. Labour to ſee the rare excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and efficacy of Faith, what is it, but a Chriſtians life while he is below? without it we cannot move one foot heaven ward; whatſoever is not of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:133432:54"/>Faith is ſin. This is that which brings in Chriſt into the Soul, it makes us one with Chriſt now, and the union that is made by Faith between Chriſt and the Soul now ſhall never be diſſolved till we enjoy him in glory. <hi>For the end of our Faith is the Salvation of our ſouls,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Bind your ſelves to a conſtant and conſcionable attendance to the Word and Ordinances of God, <hi>For Faith comes by hearing,</hi> Rom. 10.17. As death firſt entered by this door, ſo doth life; hear and your Soul ſhall live, this is that Manna on which we muſt live till we come to Canaan: As <hi>Gideons</hi> Fleece was wet when the ground about it was dry, ſo God uſually waters the Souls of them both with grace and comfort that wait on his Ordinances, when others that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them are ſtrangers to both. We read in <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48. <hi>When the Apoſtles preached, as many of the Gentiles as were ordained to eternal life believed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Be convinced of the admirable
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:133432:54"/>and infinite. Excellencies that are in God, as his Power whereby he is able to ſave, Mercy whereby he is willing to ſave, and Faithfulneſs whereby he is bound to ſave all them that come to him by Chriſt Jeſus. Now as igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is the mother of Unbelief, ſo knowledg is the foundation of Faith; he that will come to God muſt firſt know that God is, and that he is a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful rewarder of all that come him. <hi>And they that know thy name will put their truſt in thee,</hi> Pſal. 9.10.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Under all aſſaults and temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons uſe your ſelves to look up unto Chriſt, who is the author and finiſher of Faith; whatever Grace we want fetch it of him, who hath in him all treaſures, and can give us Grace for Grace. Whatever, weight either of ſin or ſuffering we are oppreſſed with, <hi>look we up to Jeſus,</hi> Heb. 12.2. And 'tis no more bat look to him and we ſhall be ſaved.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Lie at Gods feet, and be inſtant in prayer with the Father of Mercies,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:133432:55"/>and never give him reſt till he create the ſaving Grace in you; that God that heats the Ravens when they cry will hear you. O could we bemoan our dead-Heartedneſs to believe and reſt in his all-ſufficiency, whoſe power is not limited, but can as well give the life of Grace, as the life of Nature, we ſhould not for ever be denied, but ſhould at laſt feel this heavenly birth ſpring within us.</p>
            <p>And to cloſe all, if the work be dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, the fruit will be an abundant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence, our labour will not be in vain in the Lord. Chriſt will never be in debt to any for his entertainment, his preſence will quiet our hearts, purge our Conſciences, ſubdue our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, fortifie us againſt all evils, guide us by his grace, till he bring us to glory. What do we mean then that we do not ſtir up our ſelves to take hold of him; while Chriſt knocks let us ſet open the everlaſting door, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Invite him as <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 132.8. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe O Lord, and come into thy Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary.</hi>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:133432:55"/>If Chriſt ſeem ſtrange, conſtrain him, and ſay as they in <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.29. <hi>Abide with us,</hi> feaſt him with the beſt as <hi>Levi</hi> did, <hi>Lev.</hi> 5.29. Say as the Church, all our choice-ſervices we have kept only for thee. In ſhort, ſet up the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> reſolution, to give your eyes no reſt, nor ſuffer the temples of your heads to have any quiet till you have found a place in your hearts of the Lord, and an habitation for the mighty God of <hi>Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:133432:56"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Edw. Brewſter,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Crane</hi> in <hi>Paul's</hi>-Church-yard, <hi>1675.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THe <hi>Apoſtolical Hiſtory,</hi> contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Acts, Labours, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, Sermons, Diſcourſes, Miracles, Succeſſes, and Sufferings of the Holy Apoſtles, from <hi>Chriſts</hi> Aſcenſion to the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by <hi>Titus,</hi> &amp;c. By <hi>Samuel Cradock,</hi> B. D. <hi>fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Henry Smiths</hi> Sermons. <hi>4to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A Proſpect of Divine Providence. By <hi>T. C.</hi> M.A. <hi>8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Caſes of Conſcience Practically Reſolved. By the Reverend and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>J. Norman,</hi> late Miniſter of <hi>Bridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water</hi> in <hi>Sommerſet. 8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Sinner Condemned of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: being a Plea for God againſt all the Ungodly, proving them alone guilty of their own Deſtruction, <hi>&amp;c. 8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Scriptures Self-Evidence,</hi> to prove its Exiſtence, Authority in it ſelf, and ſufficiency (in its kind) to aſcertain o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb facs="tcp:133432:56"/>that it is inſpired of God to be the only Rule of Faith. Both by <hi>Thomas Ford,</hi> late Miniſter in <hi>Exon. 8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Mr. <hi>John Ball</hi> his large and ſmall Catechiſm. <hi>8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. A moſt familiar Expoſition of the Aſſemblies ſhorter Catechiſm. By <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph Allen,</hi> late Miniſter in <hi>Taunton</hi> in <hi>Sommerſet. 8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Chriſtian Advice</hi> both to Young and Old, Rich and Poor, which may ſerve as a Directory at hand, ready to direct all perſons almoſt in every eſtate and condition under 17 general uſeful Heads. By <hi>Thomas Mocket</hi> A.M.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The Doctrine of the Bible, 120.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Natural and Artificial Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>Moſes Revived:</hi> A Treatiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that it is not lawful (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſinful) for any man or woman to eat blood, <hi>viz.</hi> the life-blood of any Creature. <hi>8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. The Righteous Man's Evidence for Heaven. By <hi>Timothy Rogers.</hi> 120.</p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>Baſilius Valentinus</hi> B his laſt Will and Teſtament which was found hid under a Table of Marble behind the
<pb facs="tcp:133432:57"/>high Altar in the Cathedral Church of the Imperial City of <hi>Erford;</hi> leaving it there to be found by him whom Gods Providence ſhould make worthy of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>octav.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. The Royal Pay and Pay-Maſter. A Sermon preached before the Military Company: By <hi>William Sclater,</hi> D<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> D. Miniſter of St. <hi>James Clarkenwell. 4to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. A Uſeful Table of Expences.</p>
            <p n="16">16. <hi>Clendon</hi> on the Sabbath. <hi>4to. Hiſtories.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of <hi>Guy</hi> Earl of <hi>Warwick. quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The moſt delectable Hiſtory of <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> the Fox, the firſt and ſecond part.</p>
            <p>Fryer and the Boy: both Parts.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
